<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An alphabet of the holy proverbs of King Salomon specially from the beginning of the tenth chapter to the end of the booke for the helpe of memorie and for a more ready finding out of any whole sentence, if onely the beginning be called to mind: with a short interpretation of the more hard prouerbs, wherein also diuers translations are compared and laied together for a further helpe to vnderstanding. Collected and set down in this order with a mind desirous to procure that these holy prouerbs might be made yet more familiar euen to children by the delight of so plaine and familiar a method.</title>
            <author>Allen, Robert, fl. 1596-1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112319</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847574</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847574</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12612</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16720)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12612)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 164:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An alphabet of the holy proverbs of King Salomon specially from the beginning of the tenth chapter to the end of the booke for the helpe of memorie and for a more ready finding out of any whole sentence, if onely the beginning be called to mind: with a short interpretation of the more hard prouerbs, wherein also diuers translations are compared and laied together for a further helpe to vnderstanding. Collected and set down in this order with a mind desirous to procure that these holy prouerbs might be made yet more familiar euen to children by the delight of so plaine and familiar a method.</title>
                  <author>Allen, Robert, fl. 1596-1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 123, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Robinson for Robert Dexter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: R.A. (i.e. Robert Allen).</note>
                  <note>Errata on I7v; final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs. --  English. --  Selections.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ALPHABET of the holy PROVERBS of KING SALOMON ſpecially from the beginning of the tenth Chapter to the end of the booke: <hi>For the helpe of memorie and for a more ready fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> out of any whole ſentence, if onely the beginning be called to mind: with a ſhort interpretation of the more hard Prouerbs, wherein alſo diuers tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations are compared and laied together for a further helpe to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Collected and ſet down in this order with a mind deſirous to procure that theſe holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs might be made yet more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar euen to children by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of ſo plaine and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar a method.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The heart of a wiſe man guideth his mouth wiſely, and he addeth doctrine by his lippes.</hi>
                  <bibl>Prou. <hi>16.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>As a thorne comming into the hand of a drunkard, ſo is a parable in the mouth of fooles,</hi>
                  <bibl>Prou. <hi>29.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by Robert Robinſon for <hi>Robert Dexter.</hi> 1596.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:2"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE yong Lord THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS</hi> Lord <hi>WENTWORTH,</hi> and to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> ROBERT RICH</hi> the eldest ſonne of the right Honorable the Lord <hi>RICH,</hi> for a gratulatorie teſtimonie of duetifull affection and thankefulnes to their hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable parents: with his moſt humble &amp; heartie praier vnto <hi>GOD</hi> the onely au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and aduancer of all true nobilitie, that it maie pleaſe him of his infinite mercie to increaſe them in all ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie giftes and graces of his moſt holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, both for learning and godlineſse as may more and more adorne and bewtifie their noble degree; through our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the Lord of glorie and life, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. A. A miniſter of Gods word hath dedicated this alphabetical collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy Prouerbs of King Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:3"/>
            <head>To the Christian Reader grace and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued in the Lorde (Right chriſtian &amp; prudent reader) may it pleaſe thee to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that I thy poore well willer, doe willingly accord, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſlie profeſſe together with thy ſelf, that the moſt holie ſcriptures of God are ſet downe and deliuered vnto vs, by his owne diuine diſpenſation, in all wiſe and holy perfection, not onlie for the matter therein contained, but alſo euen for the order and manner it ſelfe, whether for phraſe of ſpeach, or for coherence of ſentence, yea euen in thoſe parts which to vs maie ſeeme leſſe coupled and knit together then the reſt.</p>
            <p>Where as therfore this preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting of the holie prouerbes for the greater part (of the whole booke) in that forme which here thou ſeeſt is far differing from the originall diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them; yea ſo as they may ſeeme
<pb facs="tcp:12612:3"/>tranſpoſed as it were out of their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and kindly ſeat &amp; ſoyle: I thought it neceſſarie by way of intreatie (euen for the pittie thou beareſt toward hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmitie) to ſeeke to obtaine that fauorable allowance at thy hands) wherin God hath vouchſafed the firſt permiſſion and leaue) which cannot otherwiſe by anie other ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be extorted from thee.</p>
            <p>Now then may it pleaſe thee to bee intreated, yea rather by humble and heartie intreatie to be ouercome, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo farre to fauor this bold enterpriſe as it may be either diſcerned by light of thy fauorable iudgement or ſhall bee found by willing diligence in the vſe of it, to be helpefull to anie, toward the more profitable reading and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of theſe diuine ſentences, in that holie order wherein the holy pen-men of the Lord haue firſt ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe.</p>
            <p>If this requeſt may ſeeme reaſonable vnto thee vpon the premiſes and alſo according to al good hope which may be conceiued herein: then alſo may the
<pb facs="tcp:12612:4"/>practiſe of the Lorde himſelfe who hath ſuccoured memorie by his owne diſpoſing of diuers portions of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; bleſſed worde in the ſame order, (as is euident in the holie language both in ſundrie <hi>Pſalmes</hi> and in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of <hi>Ieremie:</hi> and euen in the laſt Chap. of this booke of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes) this I ſay may further induce thee to conceiue ſo much the better liking of this indeuoure, at the leaſt vpon ſuch wiſe caution as the matter requireth: that is to ſay, that the compariſon bee in no wiſe equalled herein, but onlie tolerated as an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reuerend &amp; begged imitation for a helpe to our weak and frayle memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as hath bene ſaide.</p>
            <p>Beſides through the grace of God, it may bee thou ſhalt finde ſomething performed in this poore labour which of thy ſelfe thou wilt iudge, not a toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnworthie ſome peece of thy gentle acceptaunce. Namely in that the tranſlation of diuerſe ſentences is ſomewhat neerer fitted to the authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb facs="tcp:12612:4"/>text: and alſo becauſe the diuers interpretations of manie ſentences are preſented before thee in one ſhort view, for the exerciſing of thine owne modeſt iudgement and wittes in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the beſt choiſe, as in ſome fewe places (not doubting of thy good leaue) I haue not feared to doe.</p>
            <p>But that I bee not tedious; I will reſt in this perſwaſion that thou wilte yeeld to bee of this minde (in ſuch ſort as hath beene intreated) that what good and helpfull way ſoeuer (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus by the order of the letter, or by laying together all ſentences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning one &amp; the ſame matter which indeede often falleth out in this alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, but muſt be left to an other labour as touching the exact performance of it) I will reſt I ſay perſwaded, that thou wilt account euery commodious way, ſeruing to make this excellent portion of the worde of God more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarlie knowne, and to drawe it forth to a more plentifull and holie vſe, to be accepted as a grace giuen from him
<pb facs="tcp:12612:5"/>who is the only author of euery good gift and grace.</p>
            <p>Hitherto for the manner of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſpoſing of theſe holy ſentences: I beſeech thee (gentle reader) to heare me in a few words concerning the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences themſelues, as touching the moſt excellent wiſedome compriſed therein.</p>
            <p>Many make great reckoning of the ſentences of <hi>Tullie</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other fine witted heathen me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And verily they are not to bee contemned eſpecially of wiſe Chriſtians, the leaſt whereof can more holilie vnderſtande and alſo make better vſe of their owne ſentences (ſuch as poynt towards any good matter) then they could them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And alſo by ſuch ſentences ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and diſperſed in their writings we may as by certaine ruines perceiue what was the excellent frame &amp; buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of mans firſt creation.</p>
            <p>But what are thoſe their ſentences, and the rather if they bee interpreted according to their heathniſh &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb facs="tcp:12612:5"/>minde, ſeing they had not the true knowledge of God, nor of them ſelues, nor of anie thing pertaining to true religion and godlineſſe: ſeeing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their guide was but corrupt and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured light of weake and vnperfecte reaſon: what (I ſay) are all thoſe their ſentences, in compariſon of the moſt holy and perfectly wiſe prouerbes of King <hi>Salomon?</hi> Yea in compariſon of ſuch of them, wherein, for ſom appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of wordes, they might ſeeme to aime at the ſame thing with him? For all the ſentences of this our heauenly teacher (a verie true maiſter of ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces indeede) they are holie and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, proceeding from the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God in the work of his regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and new birth, through a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall enlightning &amp; ſanctifying of the heart, tongue and penne of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes, whoſe faithful labours are met in the publiſhing of them for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Church of God: but the ſentences of heathen men are in themſelues vnholy, earthly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb facs="tcp:12612:6"/>The ſentences of King <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> are all grounded vpon the true knowledge of God, in the faith of Chriſt Ieſus our redeemer &amp; ſauiour, who is the only true light of men, and the verie life, ſoule &amp; ſpirit of all ſonud doctrine and perfect inſtruction: they haue alſo their ſcope and drift, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God cheefely, and then the faith and repentance of Gods people vnder the aſſured hope of the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, and of the inheritance of eternall life in the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: but the ſentences of the heathen are nothing ſo, but wanting all ſure ground they teach rather a ſhadow of vertue, then vertue indeede, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without a better teaching all the fruite vaniſheth awaie in an idle and fruitleſſe ſpeculation.</p>
            <p>Moreouer as the ſentences of King <hi>Sulomon</hi> guide vs certainly to the right end of faith, euen the glorie of God &amp; ſaluation of our ſoules, ſo do they laie out and perfectly deſcribe vnto vs the onely right waie of holie obedience
<pb facs="tcp:12612:6"/>and dutie both to God and man: but all the goodlie direction of humaine and philoſophical vertues dieth in the ſeruing of mens owne turnes, eyther for the gayning of worldly prayſe or worldly honour, or for ſome other like end, in ſo much as it is truely ſaid that (the matter truely ſcanned) all their vertues are but ſhining and glittering ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Wherefore nowe vppon ſuch vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall compariſon let euerie of vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke our harts to haue theſe moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſentences among the reſt of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſcriptures in more high and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious eſtimation in finitely aboue all ſentences of heathen men. And to this purpoſe I beſeech thee to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider with mee that whatſoeuer may haue ſpeciall force to moue the minde to deſire a thing abſent, to ioy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it being preſent, and to hope for after fruite by it, they all doe meete in the gratious ſentences of King <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (conſidered together) as in one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. For what moueth the minde to
<pb facs="tcp:12612:7"/>deſire any thing, but fame, ſweetenes, pleaſure, riches, bewtie and ſuch like? What delighteth but the ſame things, &amp; therewithall in the matter of ſpeach and inſtruction, theſe three thinges plainnes, breuitie, and varietie? And what afterfruite is more comfortable then ioy after ſorrow, ſaftie after dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, glorie after reproch, and if there be any other like vnto theſe.</p>
            <p>Behold then what fame (the fame of our Sauiour only excepted) was euer ſo greate as the fame of <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? How ſweete are his wordes as ointment &amp; ſweet perfume to reioyce the heart by all kinde of ſweete coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell? How pleaſant and bewtiful like apples of golde with pictures of ſiluer? How rich, euen like the chaine about the necke, yea like the diadem and glorious crowne vpon the heade? Againe doe not K. <hi>Salomons</hi> prouerbes moſt briefely containe moſt ample &amp; large matter? doe they not leade vs as it were by the hand into verie high turrets whence by a quick vew we may
<pb facs="tcp:12612:7"/>eaſilie behould manie thinges a far off which would aſke greater paines &amp; longer time to bee leſſe diſcerned of the wiſeſt among vs, walking through the low vallie of our owne thoughts? Touching varietie, what a large gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is here vnlocked vnto vs, full of all ſorts of ſweet fruit &amp; pleaſant flowers: what a ſtore-houſe for al plentie of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall foode and vittaile? what a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drope with robes fit to decke the mindes of all that reſorte to it like princes children? what a iewell-houſe of all kinde of pretious iewels to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſoule withall? what a libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of all flowers and elegancies of the beſt learning as in one litle enchiridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſhedule to repleniſh thy minde with holie vnderſtanding &amp; wiſdome? And touching the fruite therefore of theſe ſo excellent ſentences wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; digeſted in the mind and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie practiſed in the ordering of the life, who can reckon them vp in order? On<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly this ſhall now be ſaide in generall that bleſſed are they of God who will
<pb facs="tcp:12612:8"/>dayly exerciſe themſelues in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, remembrance, vſe &amp; practiſe of them as of any other the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God. Bleſſed are thoſe Parents which wil wiſely &amp; carefully acquaint their children with them, as the verie manner of ſetting them downe in the name of a father moſt louingly and carefully teaching his childe doth declare that it is the will of God they ſhould do ſo: and bleſſed for euer are thoſe children who hearkning to their wiſe and godly Parents wil learne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and wiſdome from them.</p>
            <p>Now finally this booke is dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more particularlie to the honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble children aboue mentioned, to this end (beſide the reaſon expreſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) that by one duetie tendered to them, many by occaſion therof, might be made partakers of a common bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. And thus good reader, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende thee to the Lorde, beſeeching him moſt humblie for our Lord Ieſus Chriſtes ſake to deliuer vs more and
<pb facs="tcp:12612:8"/>more from all vanitie of minde, and to preſerue our harts with daily increaſe of all heauenly grace both for wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and godlineſſe, vnto his euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting kingdome of glorie Amen.</p>
            <p>Thine in the Lord both cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thy faithfull prayer and alſo praying withal his heart for thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:9"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prouerbs Chap. 4. verſes 3. &amp;c.</bibl>
               <p>3. <hi>VVHen I was a Child with my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, tender &amp; deare in the ſight of my mother;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. <hi>He taught mee and ſaid vnto me; let thine heart hold faſt my words; keepe my comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and liue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. <hi>Get wiſedome, get vnder ſtanding; forget thou not neither decline from the words of my mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. <hi>Forſake her not, and ſhe will keepe thee; loue her and ſhe will preſerue thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7. <hi>Wiſedome is the chiefe thing, get wiſedome therefore; yea with all thy poſſeſſion get vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>8. <hi>Exalt her and ſhee will exalt thee; ſhee will ſurely make thee honorable, if thou wilt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>9. <hi>She will giue a comely ornament vnto thy head, yea she will giue thee a crowne of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Chap. 22. verſe 6.</bibl>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>TEach a child in the trade of his way, &amp; euen when he ſhall be old he will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from it.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:9"/>
            <head>AN ALPHABET <hi>of the holy Prouerbs of King Salomon</hi> eſpecially from the beginning <hi>of the tenth Chapter to the ende</hi> of the Booke.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A B</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Boue euerie watch, watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>(or keepe)</hi> thy heart, for from it are the out-goings <hi>(or iſſues, that is to ſay, the actions)</hi> of life. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſe.</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p>A brother offended <hi>(to wit, by the euill and vnfaithfull dealing of a brother) is harder to winne</hi> then a ſtrong Citie, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are like the barre of a pallace, <hi>or caſtle, Chap.</hi> 18. <hi>verſe.</hi> 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A C</head>
                  <p>ACcuſe thou not a ſeruant to his maſter, <hi>(or as the word ſignifieth, hurt him not with thy tongue; to wit by any vniuſt or vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table complaint)</hi> leſt he curſe thee, &amp; thou be founde to haue offended. <hi>Chap.</hi> 30.10. <hi>Read more in the letter. T.</hi> The wordes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur. &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12612:10"/>
                  <p>A child is knowne by his dooings whether his worke be pure and right. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.11. <hi>Or thus,</hi> let euen the childe make himſelfe knowne <hi>(or bewray himſelfe)</hi> whether his worke be pure, and whether it be right. <hi>That is, let euery one euen from his childhood auoid all hypocriſie and diſſimulation, acquainting himſelfe to deale alwaies ſimplie and plainely both in word and indeed. To the which ende may that alſo be referred which followeth in the next verſe:</hi> The Lord hath made euen both theſe, the eare hearing &amp; the eye ſeeing. <hi>Ch.</hi> 20.12 <hi>And therefore (by good conſequence) he both knoweth howe and alſo vvill in time diſcouer and lay open all counterfet dealing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A continuall dropping in the day of ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie raine, and a contentious woman are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. He that hideth her <hi>(that is, vvhich go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to hide her ill quality, yea though it be by vviſe admonition and louing counſell)</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the winde <hi>(that is, he looſeth his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, to vvit, vnleſſe God giue ſpeciall grace and bleſſing)</hi> for ſhe will vtter herſelfe as oile <hi>(or ointment)</hi> in his right hand. <hi>The ſmell vvhereof cannot be kept in. Chap.</hi> 27.15.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A D</head>
                  <p>A Deſire accompliſhed <hi>(that is, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing deſired beeing novve at hand and preſently inioyed, specially the spirituall graces
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12612:10"/>and bleſſings of God in aſſarance of his fauour)</hi> deliteth the ſoule: but it is an abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to fooles to depart from euill. <hi>So farre off is it from them to deſire to doe the vvill of God, Chap.</hi> 13.19.</p>
                  <p>A diſcreet ſeruant ſhall haue rule ouer a lewde ſonne, and he ſhall deuide the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among the brethren. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.2.</p>
                  <p>A diuine ſentence ſhall be in the lippes of the king: his mouth ſhall not tranſgreſſe in iudgement. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.10. <hi>Or thus.</hi> Let a diuine ſentence <hi>(or moſt ſage, prudent and ſharpeſighted vviſedome)</hi> be in the lippes of the King: <hi>(that is, let him alwaies haue a holie care to ſpeake vviſely and diſcreetly, but chieflie then vvhen he ſhall ſit iudicially to giue ſentence in vveightie cauſes, according to that vvhich follovveth)</hi> let not his mouth tranſgreſſe in iudgement. <hi>Reade in</hi> A. <hi>A true vveight. &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 16.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A F</head>
                  <p>A Faithfull man <hi>(or as the hebrew ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth)</hi> a man of much faithfulnes <hi>(or a very faithfull man)</hi> ſhal abound in bleſſings; but he that maketh haſt to be rich ſhall not be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28.20.</p>
                  <p>A faithfull witneſſe deliuereth ſoules: but a deceiuer ſpeaketh <hi>(or breatheth foorth)</hi> lies <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.25.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:12612:11"/>
                  <p>A faithfull witneſſe <hi>(the hebrew is more ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant, as before)</hi> A verie faithfull witneſſe will not lie: but a falſe witneſſe will breath out lies. <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.5.</p>
                  <p>A falſe tongue, <hi>(that is, a man of a falſe or deceitfull tongue)</hi> hateth thoſe whome he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicteth, <hi>(or whome he woulde deſtroy)</hi> and a flattering mouth cauſeth ruine. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.28.</p>
                  <p>A falſe witneſſe <hi>(in heb: a witneſſe of falſe matters)</hi> ſhall not be vnpuniſhed: and he that ſpeaketh lies <hi>(or breatheth foorth, that is, lightlie and vnaduiſedly vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth lies,)</hi> ſhall not eſcape. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.5. <hi>And verſe.</hi> 9. He ſhall periſh. <hi>So alſo Chap.</hi> 21.28.</p>
                  <p>A falſe witneſſe <hi>(in Heb. A witneſſe of lies)</hi> ſhall periſh: but hee that heareth <hi>(that is, the well aduiſed witneſſe)</hi> ſhall ſpeake for euer, <hi>or continually: to wit, with credit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Affliction <hi>(or rather euill)</hi> followeth ſinners, <hi>(to wit as purſuing and dogging them)</hi> but that which is good recompenceth the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.21.</p>
                  <p>A foole deſpiſeth his fathers inſtruction: but he that regardeth correction is prudent. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.5.</p>
                  <p>A foole hath no delight in vnderſtanding, but in that onely which diſcouereth it ſelfe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12612:11"/>to his heart. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.2.</p>
                  <p>A foole powreth foorth all his minde; but a wiſe man keepeth it in till afterward, <hi>(or reſtraineth it)</hi> as touching the latter part. <hi>That is, he reſerueth it for the fitteſt ſeaſon. Chap.</hi> 29.11.</p>
                  <p>A fooles anger ſhall be knowne in a day, <hi>(that is, in a ſhorte time)</hi> but he that is wiſe couereth ſhame. <hi>That is, hee refraineth his anger which otherwiſe woulde breake foorth to his ſhame. Chap.</hi> 12.16.</p>
                  <p>A fooles lippes come with ſtrife, <hi>(or make ſtrife)</hi> and his mouth calleth for ſtripes. <hi>To wit, to his owne ſore hurte, as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the next verſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A fooles mouth is his owne deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and his lips are a ſnare for his ſoule. <hi>Ch.</hi> 18.6.7.</p>
                  <p>A fooliſh ſonne is the calamitie of his father, <hi>(that is, he is the cauſe of greate trouble to him)</hi> and the contentions of a wife are like a continuall dropping. <hi>To witte, which marreth and rotteth all, Chap.</hi> 19.13.</p>
                  <p>A friende loueth at all times: and a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is borne for aduerſitie. <hi>That is, to help and ſuccour in aduerſitie. Or thus,</hi> and a brother is borne <hi>(or ſheweth himſelfe to be a brother in deede)</hi> in aduerſitie. <hi>Chap.</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12612:12"/>17.17</p>
                  <p>A froward perſon <hi>(or as the wordes of the text are)</hi> A man of frowardneſſe <hi>(that is, ſuch a one as is giuen to much froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes)</hi> ſoweth ſtrife, and a tale-teller maketh di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion among Princes, <hi>(or rather thus)</hi> ſeparateth a chiefe friend, <hi>Chap:</hi> 16.28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A G</head>
                  <p>AGe is a crowne of glorie, when it is found in the way of righteouſneſſe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 1631.</p>
                  <p>A gift in ſecret pacifieth anger, and a gift in the boſome greate wrath <hi>(or as the word ſignifieth)</hi> the vehement <hi>(or migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie)</hi> heat of wrath. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.14.</p>
                  <p>A good man getteth fauour of the Lord: but he will condemne the man of wicked imaginations, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Or rather thus;</hi> The fauour of the Lorde preferreth <hi>(or aduanceth)</hi> a good man: but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the wicked, <hi>(or miſcheeuous)</hi> man.</p>
                  <p>A good name is to be choſen aboue greate riches, and louing fauoure is aboue filuer and aboue gold. <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.1. <hi>or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus.</hi> A name <hi>(or fame,</hi> King <hi>Salomon meaneth indeede a good name or report, to wit, in the church of God and among good men)</hi> is to be choſen aboue greate riches, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12612:12"/>
                     <hi>(that is, gratious credit and eſtimation)</hi> is better then ſiluer and gould.</p>
                  <p>A gratious woman attayneth honour, as ſtrong men attayne to riches, <hi>Chap</hi> 11.16.</p>
                  <p>A haughtie looke and a proude heart, yea euen the light of the wicked <hi>(that is, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſeemeth moſt excellent vnto them, or hath the greateſt appearance)</hi> is ſinne. <hi>Or thus:</hi> yea the enterpriſe <hi>(or endeauour)</hi> of the wicked is ſinne. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A I</head>
                  <p>A Ioyfull heart cauſeth good health, <hi>(or yeldeth good help to the medicin orphiſick whether it be bodilie or for the ſoule)</hi> but a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull minde <hi>(that is, a minde or ſpirit cruſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed with ſorrow)</hi> drieth the bones. <hi>Cha.</hi> 17.22.</p>
                  <p>A ioyfull heart maketh a cheareful counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but by the ſorrow of the heart the minde is broken <hi>(or chruſhed as before,) Ch</hi> 15.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A K</head>
                  <p>A King by iudgement <hi>(that is, by execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting iudgment)</hi> mainteineth <hi>(or eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth)</hi> the earth, (<hi>as Pſa.</hi> 75.3.) but a man of offeringes, <hi>(that is, receiuing giftes offered, ſuch one as counteth all fiſh that commes to net &amp;c.)</hi> deſtroyeth it. <hi>Cha.</hi> 29.4.</p>
                  <p>A King that iudgeth the poore in truth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12612:13"/>
                     <hi>(or faithfully)</hi> his throne ſhal be eſtabliſhed for euer. <hi>Ch.</hi> 29.14.</p>
                  <p>A King that ſiettth in the throne of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, chaſeth away all euill with his eyes. <hi>That is, God giueth a ſpeciall bleſſing to ſuch Kinges as be carefull in their owne perſonnes to ſee that iuſtice take place. Cha.</hi> 20.8.</p>
                  <p>All <hi>(or as the conſtruction well beareth)</hi> euerie one that is proude in hearte is an abhomination to the Lorde: though hand ioyne to hand he ſhall not be vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <hi>(that is, no helpe or aſſiſtance ſhall deliuer him from the puniſhing hande of God.) Chapter.</hi> 16. <hi>5. See in the letter. T. Though hand. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All the brethren of the poore doe hate him, yea euen his friende, <hi>(to wit, he that was his friend in appearance)</hi> they all ſtand aloofe from him; though he be inſtant with wordes, yet they will not be neare. <hi>That is, they will not be intreated to helpe him Chap.</hi> 19.7.</p>
                  <p>All the dayes of the afflicted <hi>(or poore man, to wit, ſuch one as is not content with his eſtate)</hi> are euill <hi>(that is, they are grieuous and irkeſome to him)</hi> but to him that hath a good conſcience, they are a continuall <hi>(or daily)</hi> feaſt. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.15.</p>
                  <p>All the wayes of a man are cleane in his owne eyes <hi>(or thus in an other verie apt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12612:13"/>conſtruction) Howſoeuer</hi> man as touching all his wayes, is cleane in his owne eyes <hi>(that is, ſeemeth ſo to himſelfe)</hi> Yet the Lord pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the ſpirites. <hi>As though he ſhould ſay noe counterfaite thing ſhall go for paiment with him: Cha.</hi> 16.2. <hi>Reade in. T. The preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A M</head>
                  <p>A Man cannot be eſtabliſhed by wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but the roote of the righteous ſhall not be remoued. <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.2.</p>
                  <p>A man deſtitute of vnderſtanding touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hand, <hi>(or clappeth hands)</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth ſuertie for his neighbour. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.18. <hi>He reproueth raſh &amp; vnaduiſed ſuerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A man of much anger ſhall ſuffer puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and though thou deliuer him, yet will his anger come againe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.19. <hi>Reade in the letter C. the next verſe to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten thy ſonne. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A mans gift <hi>(to wit, whether we take it for that inward gifte wherewith God hath graced a man, or for that externall gift or preſent which he hath inabled him to gratifie any with all)</hi> it inlargeth him <hi>(that is, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth him out of ſtraites)</hi> and bringeth him before greate men) <hi>that is, before men of greate ſtate and dignitie, Chap.</hi> 18.16.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12612:14"/>
                  <p>A man ſhalbe commended according to his wiſdome: but the froward of heart ſhal be deſpiſed. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.8.</p>
                  <p>A man ſhall be ſatiate with good things by the fruite of his mouth: and the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of a mans handes will God giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Or rather thus; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the naturall conſtruction of the wordes.</hi> A good man ſhall be ſatiate by the fruite of his mouth, the recompence of his handes <hi>(that is, of his workes)</hi> ſhall he cauſe to returne to himſelfe. <hi>That is, he ſhall receiue it to his owne benefit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A man ſhall eate good thinges by the fruite of his mouth: <hi>(or as before)</hi> A good man ſhall eat the fruite of his mouth <hi>(that is, he himſelfe ſhall enioy the benefit of his good and gratious and well ordred speach)</hi> but the ſoule of treſpaſſers ſhall <hi>eate the fruite</hi> of violence. <hi>That is, it ſhall ſuffer vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence. Ch:</hi> 13.2.</p>
                  <p>A man that beareth falſe witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his neighboure is like an hammer and a ſworde, and a ſharpe arrow. <hi>Chap:</hi> 25.18.</p>
                  <p>A man that boaſteth of falſe liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>(in heb: of a gifte of falſhood, that is, of a falſe gifte, that is, ſuch a one as promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth but performeth not)</hi> is like cloudes and winde without raine. <hi>Ch:</hi> 25.14.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12612:14"/>
                  <p>A man that doeth violence againſt the blood, <hi>(that is, the life)</hi> of a man <hi>(or as ſome other tranſlate, though all tending to one and the ſame ende)</hi> A man that is opreſſed <hi>(that is to ſay, earneſtly purſued by the auenger of bloode, to wit, according to the lawe of God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in that behalfe)</hi> for the bloude of a man, let him fly to the graue, let no man ſtay <hi>(or ſupport him) that is, let no man hinder ſpeedie execution of the murtherer. Cha.</hi> 28.17.</p>
                  <p>A man that flattereth his neighbor, ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a nette for his feete. <hi>Chap.</hi> 29.5.</p>
                  <p>A man that hardeneth his necke, hauing beene often rebuked, ſhall be <hi>(as one)</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly cruſhed to pieces, ſo as he cannot be cured, <hi>Cha.</hi> 29.1.</p>
                  <p>A man that hath friendes ought to ſhew him ſelfe friendly: for a friende <hi>(that is, ſome frende-bodie as we call him)</hi> is nearer <hi>(that is, he is more entirely affected, and beareth more hartie good will)</hi> then a brother <hi>(that is, then ſome naturall brother how neare ſoeuer they are linked by boud of conſanguinity and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Chap.</hi> 18.24.</p>
                  <p>A man that loueth wiſedome reioyceth his father but he that ſee deth <hi>(or companieth with)</hi> harlotes, waſteth his ſubſtance. <hi>(and ſo is a grief and burthen to him. Ch.</hi> 29.3.</p>
                  <p>A man that refraineth not his appetite, <hi>(or which hath no rule ouer his ſpirite and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection)</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12612:15"/>is like a citie broken downe and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a wall. <hi>Ch.</hi> 25.28.</p>
                  <p>A man that wandereth out of the waye of wiſedome ſhall reſt <hi>(or ceaſe, to wit, from his erring)</hi> in the congregation <hi>(or company,)</hi> of the deade. <hi>That is, he ſhall haue his portion with them whoſe thoughtes periſhe and who haue no part in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. Ch.</hi> 21.16.</p>
                  <p>A man will giue his riches for the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of his life: <hi>or thus.</hi> The riches of a man ſhall be the ranſome of his life: <hi>(that is, it falleth out oftentimes that the rich man will he, nill he, muſt part with his riches to ſaue his life):</hi> but the poore man heareth no reproofe. <hi>(that is, he is quiet while the rich is ſifted, to wit, in times of warrefare and tirannous gouernmente: ſo that riches as well as pouertie hath certaine peculiare diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities. Ch.</hi> 13.8.</p>
                  <p>A man with a wicked eye, <hi>(that is, which hath an euill eye)</hi> haſteth to get riches, but he knoweth not, <hi>(that is, he willingly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not)</hi> that pouerty ſhall come vpon him. <hi>Ch:</hi> 28.22. <hi>yet this contrarie euent befalleth many of thoſe which doe moſt greedily hunte afterworldly wealth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A N</head>
                  <p>AN angrie man ſtirreth vp ſtrife, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12612:15"/>a furious man aboundeth in tranſgreſſion. <hi>Ch.</hi> 29.22.</p>
                  <p>An angrie man ſtirreth vp ſtrife, but he that is ſlowe to wrath <hi>(or long ſuffering)</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſtrife. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.18.</p>
                  <p>Anger is cruell and wrath is raging: but who can ſtand before enuie? <hi>Ch:</hi> 27.4.</p>
                  <p>An heritage haſtily gotten at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſhall not be bleſſed in the end thereof. <hi>Chap:</hi> 20.21.</p>
                  <p>An hipocrite with his mouth hurteth his neighboure; but the righteous ſhall be deliuered by knowledge. <hi>That is, by wiſe caution and diligente takeing heede to the worde of God. Ch:</hi> 11.9.</p>
                  <p>Anſwere not a foole accordinge to his fooliſhneſſe, leaſt thou alſo be like him.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer a foole according to his fooliſhnes, leaſt he be wiſe in his owne conceite: <hi>that is, anſwer not foliſhlie, but with wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as his follie requireth to be anſwered Ch:</hi> 26.4.5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A P</head>
                  <p>A Poore man which oppreſſeth the poore, <hi>is like</hi> the raging <hi>(or ſweeping)</hi> raine which leaueth no foode. <hi>Chapter:</hi> 28.3.</p>
                  <p>Applie thine hearte to inſtruction and thine eares to the wordes of knowledge.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12612:16"/>
                     <hi>Chap:</hi> 23.12.</p>
                  <p>A prince which is deſtitute of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and a great oppreſſor <hi>(ſhall ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his daies)</hi> but he that hateth couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>(or gaine, to wit, vnlawfull and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked gaine)</hi> ſhall prolong his daies, <hi>Ch</hi> 28.16.</p>
                  <p>A Prince is pacified by longe ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a ſoft toungue breaketh the bones. <hi>That is, it mitigateth and alayeth the anger of the very hard harted man, Ch:</hi> 25.15.</p>
                  <p>A prudent man foreſeeing the plague <hi>(or euil whatſoeuer it be,)</hi> hideth himſelf <hi>(to wit, by humbling himſelf &amp; ſeekeing mercy at the hands of God)</hi> but the fooliſh going on ſtill <hi>(to wit without repentance)</hi> are puniſhed. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And againe.</hi> 27.12.</p>
                  <p>A reproofe entereth more into him that hath vnderſtanding <hi>(or daunteth him more)</hi> then an hundreth ſtripes into a foole: <hi>(or, then if thou ſhouldeſt beate a foole a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth times. Ch:</hi> 17.10.</p>
                  <p>A rewarde <hi>(or gift)</hi> is as a pretious ſtone verie pleaſant in the eyes of them that are greedy of it: it proſpereth whitherſoeuer it loketh. <hi>(Or tendeth) Ch:</hi> 17.8.</p>
                  <p>A righteous man falling downe <hi>(or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, turning aſide, that is, declining from his righteouſneſſe whether for feare or through hope of preferment)</hi> before the wicked, is like a troubled well, <hi>(to wit, when the mied
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12612:16"/>is roared and raiſed vp by treading in it)</hi> or a corrupted ſpring. <hi>Greate therefore is the ſinne both of the one and of the other: but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially of thoſe that doe trouble and mar the cleare spring. Chap:</hi> 25.26.</p>
                  <p>A righteous man hateth the lying word <hi>(or matter)</hi> but it cauſeth the wicked to ſtinke, and putteth him to ſhame. <hi>To witte, when his vvickedneſſe is found out in that he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and delighteth to ſlaunder &amp; lie. Ch:</hi> 13.5.</p>
                  <p>A righteou sman regardeth the life of his beaſt, but the tender mercies of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>(that is, the mercies which they acount tender)</hi> are cruell. <hi>Ch:</hi> 12.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A S</head>
                  <p>A Sciſmaticall perſon ſeeketh for that which he deſireth <hi>(or that which is to his owne liking)</hi> he will haue to doo in euerie weightie matter. <hi>Ch:</hi> 18.1.</p>
                  <p>A ſcorner loueth not him that rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him, neither will he goe to the wiſe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.12.</p>
                  <p>A ſcorner ſeeketh wiſdome and it is not; <hi>(that is, it will not be founde)</hi> but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is eaſie to him that will vnderſtand. <hi>That is, it willingly preſenteth and offereth it ſelfe vnto him. Ch.</hi> 14.6.</p>
                  <p>A ſeditious perſon ſeeketh onely euill: <hi>or thus,</hi> An euill perſon ſeeketh onely ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12612:17"/>
                     <hi>(or rebellion) to wit againſt the holy lawes of God:</hi> wherefore, a cruell meſſenger ſhall be ſent againſt him. <hi>That is, God will in due time one way or other take vengeance of him. Ch:</hi> 17.11.</p>
                  <p>A ſeruant is not chaſticed with wordes, <hi>(that is with wordes alone, but will aſke ſtripes as we ſay)</hi> when though he vnderſtand yet he anſwereth not. <hi>That is, though knowing his maiſters will, he doth it not. Ch:</hi> 29.19.</p>
                  <p>A ſlouthfull hand maketh poore: <hi>or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus,</hi> He that worketh with a deceiptful hand becommeth poore, <hi>(that is, this curſe of God is vpon him:)</hi> but the hand of the diligent maketh rich. <hi>To vvit, through the bleſſing of God vpon their honeſt and faithfull dealing. Chap.</hi> 10.4.</p>
                  <p>A ſoft anſwere turneth away wrath: but a grieuous worde ſtirreth vp anger. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.1.</p>
                  <p>A ſounde heart; <hi>or rather,</hi> A healing heart, <hi>(that is, a heart readie to ſhewe mercy tovvard the healing of others)</hi> is the life of all the fleſh <hi>(that is, of the vvhole bodie,)</hi> but enuying is the rotting of the bones. <hi>That is, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunteth the inmoſt and moſt ſtronge partes. Chap.</hi> 14.30.</p>
                  <p>A ſtone is heauie <hi>(or hath heauineſſe)</hi> and the ſand hath weightineſſe: but a fooles wrath is heauier then them both. <hi>Cha.</hi> 27.3.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12612:17"/>
                     <hi>Read alſo the next verſe.</hi> Anger is cruel. &amp;c. <hi>Or thus,</hi> Cruelty is in anger and an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing in wrath: and who can ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enuie?</p>
                  <p>As a bird that wandereth from her neſt, ſo is a man which wandereth from his place. <hi>Chap.</hi> 27.8. <hi>Such a one can haue no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance eyther for comforte to his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or for ſafetie vnder protection of the Lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As a dog turneth againe to his owne vomit, ſo a foole turneth againe to <hi>(or reitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth)</hi> his fooliſhneſſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.11.</p>
                  <p>As a iewell of golde in a ſwines ſnowte, ſo is a faire woman that lacketh diſcretion, <hi>(or reiecteth reaſon.) Chap.</hi> 26.11.</p>
                  <p>As are the cold waters to a weary foule, ſo is good newes from a farre countrie. <hi>Ch.</hi> 25.25.</p>
                  <p>As a roring Lion, and a hungry Bear <hi>(or a beare ranging about, to wit, for his pray being hungry)</hi> ſo is a wicked ruler ouer the poore people. <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.11.</p>
                  <p>As a thorne comming vp into the hand of a drunkard, ſo is a parable in the mouth of fooles: He <hi>(that is the drunken man)</hi> troubleth all, he giueth the foole his payment, yea he giueth his reward to all that paſſe by. <hi>(That is, he maketh no difference, he troubleth one as well as an other. Chap.</hi> 26.9.10. <hi>Se in the letter. T. The excellent, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12612:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>As he that feineth himſelfe mad <hi>(or as a mad man)</hi> caſteth firebrandes, arrowes and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall thinges; <hi>(that is, thinges miſchieuous and deadly)</hi> So is euery one that dealeth deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with his neighbour, and ſaieth am I not in ſport? <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.18.19.</p>
                  <p>As in water face anſwereth to face, ſo doth the heart of man to man. <hi>That is, but darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) Chap.</hi> 27.19. <hi>Read.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. <hi>and Iames</hi> 1.23.24. <hi>And Ier.</hi> 17.9. The heart of man is deceitful aboue all things. <hi>Yet ſo as by means, ſuch as are, countenance, speach, and courſe of actions it may be in part diſcerned: and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally all haue the ſame corruption of nature in common though in ſome it lurketh and keepeth in more cloſely then in other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As is the fining pot for ſiluer, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace for golde, ſo is euerie man according to his dignitie. <hi>Reade in the letter T. The fining pot, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As is the fining pot for ſiluer, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace for golde, ſo the Lord trieth the hearts. <hi>That is, he alone doth both diſcouer the hidden corruption of all, and alſo doth cleanſe &amp; purge out the inward droſſe that is in the heartes of his children by the fire of his ſpirit, Chap.</hi> 17.3.</p>
                  <p>As ointment &amp; perfume reioyce the heart, ſo doth the ſweetneſſe of a mans friende more then his owne counſell. <hi>Chap.</hi> 27, 9.</p>
                  <p>As righteouſneſſe leadeth to life: ſo he that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12612:18"/>followeth euill ſeeketh his owne death, <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Reade in T. next after, The wicked worketh, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As ſiluer droſſe ouerlaid vpon an earthen veſſell, ſo are burning <hi>(or fauning)</hi> lippes <hi>(that is, ſuch as pretend hotte and earneſt loue)</hi> and an euill heart. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.23.</p>
                  <p>As the cloſing vp of a pretious ſtone in an heape of ſtones, <hi>(or rather thus)</hi> As he that putteth a ſtone into a ſling <hi>(or into any engine made to throw ſtones)</hi> ſo is he that giueth honor to a foole. <hi>That is, he doth but imbolden him to doe hurt. Chap.</hi> 26.8.</p>
                  <p>As the cole maketh burning coles and woode a fier, ſo the contentious man is apt to kindle ſtrife. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.21. <hi>Read in W. Without woode. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As the colde of the ſnow, <hi>(that is, as the water which is as cold as the ſnow, or ſnowe water it ſelfe)</hi> in the time of narueſt, <hi>(to wit, when a man drinketh it to coole his thirſt, &amp;c.)</hi> ſo is a faithfull meſſenge to them that ſend him: for he refreſheth, <hi>(or reſtoreth, and as it were reuiueth)</hi> the ſoule of his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. <hi>That is, of thoſe that thinke long to heare good newes while the matter, (beeing weighty) is yet in ſuſpence &amp; hangeth doubtful. Ch.</hi> 25.13.</p>
                  <p>As the dore turneth vpon the henges, ſo doth the ſlouthfull man vpon his bed. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.14. <hi>Read more in</hi> T. <hi>The ſlouthfull, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12612:19"/>
                  <p>As the northwind driueth away raine, ſo doth an angry countenance the ſlaundering tongue. <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.23. <hi>A holy and good ſenſe. Neuertheleſſe the wordes vvill beare an other ſignification &amp; conſtruction vvhich is vvorthy to be conſidered of, as it follovveth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As the northerne winde ingendreth <hi>(or breedeth raine)</hi> ſo doth the tongue of the whiſperer <hi>(or priuie ſlaunderer)</hi> cauſe an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie countenance. <hi>To vvit, againſt thoſe that are miſreported and ſlaundered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As the ſnowe in ſommer, and as raine in harueſt, ſo is honour vnſeemely for a foole. <hi>Or not conuenient that it ſhould be giuen vnto him. Chap.</hi> 26.1.</p>
                  <p>As the ſparrow <hi>(is vvont)</hi> to wander heere and there, and the ſwallowe to flie about, ſo the curſe that is cauſeleſſe ſhall not come. <hi>That is, it shall not light vpon him that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtlie curſed. Chap.</hi> 26.2.</p>
                  <p>As the whirlewind paſſeth, ſo is the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked no more: but the righteous man is as an euerlaſting foundation. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Read in</hi> T. <hi>after. That vvhich, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As they that lift vp the legges of the lame, ſo is a parable in a fooles mouth. <hi>That is, he vſeth it verie vntovvardlie. Chap.</hi> 26.7. <hi>Or as ſome tranſlate.</hi> Take away the ornament of the legges <hi>(ſuch as are pantaples or baskins. &amp;c.)</hi> From him that is lame <hi>(to vvitte, as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12612:19"/>thinges vvhich hee cannot vvell vſe ſo long as hee continueth lame)</hi> ſo alſo take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the parable which is in the fooles mouth. <hi>That is, shevve the right vſe of it to the reproofe of his abuſe. Chap.</hi> 26.7.</p>
                  <p>As vineger is to the teeth <hi>(to wit, in that it ſetteth them on edge)</hi> and as ſmoake to the eies, ſo is the ſlouthfull bodie to them that ſend him. <hi>That is, he is a griefe to them by his delay, Chap.</hi> 10.26. <hi>Reade more in T. The ſlouthfull. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As well <hi>(that is, in like manner)</hi> ſinneth he whoſe minde diſcerneth not that which is not good, as he that haſteth with his feete. <hi>That is, as he eaſily ſtumbleth, who going a iourney chooſeth not his way or looketh not to his feete, ſo without knowledge and care to diſcorne betwixt good and euill a man ſhall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely breake the commaundement of God and hurt his owne ſoule. A further declaration whereof followeth in the next verſe. Reade in T. The fooliſhneſſe. &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 19.2.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A T</head>
                  <p>A True weight and ballance are of the Lord: <hi>or thus.</hi> The beame &amp; the ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of iudgement <hi>(that is the ſcoales and what ſoeuer ſerueth to faſten to the beams for equal counterpaiſe)</hi> are of the Lord: <hi>that is, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12612:20"/>King muſt doe iuſtice as he will anſwere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, becauſe all iudgment is his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. For ſo it followeth)</hi> all the weightes of the bagg are his worke, <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.11. <hi>And that this verſe is ſo to be vnderſtand it may appeare by many ſentences of the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before and after. Reade in A. A diuine ſentence &amp;c. And in in I. It is an &amp;c. And in R. Righteous lippes. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A V</head>
                  <p>A Vertuous woman is the croune of her huſband, but ſhe that putteth him to ſhame is as corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>(or rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes)</hi> in his bones. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.4. <hi>That is, ſhe taketh away the ioy of his life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A VV</head>
                  <p>A Wholſome tongue <hi>(or, The wholſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the tongue)</hi> is as a tree of life <hi>(that is, ſuch a tree as beareth medicinable and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling leaues &amp;c.</hi> but the frowardneſſe thereof is as a breach which the winde maketh. <hi>That is, it is verio miſcheeuous, it turneth vp roote and rinde as we ſay. Chap.</hi> 15.4.</p>
                  <p>A wicked <hi>(or boiſterous)</hi> man by faier words deceiueth his neighbour, that he may lead him in a way that is not good. <hi>That is, which is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious or for his profit:</hi> he ſhutteth his eies to deuiſe wicked things, he minceth with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12612:20"/>his lippes and bringeth miſchiefe to paſſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.29.30.</p>
                  <p>A wicked man diggeth vp euill <hi>(that is, he is painfull about it and maketh as it were his ſecret pitfals)</hi> and in his lippes there is as it were burning fire. <hi>That is, he is euerie way pernicious and hurtfull. He ſpeaketh of ſuch a one as regardeth neither God nor man but is a lawleſſe and deſperate fellowe, Chap.</hi> 16.27.</p>
                  <p>A wicked man harde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth his face <hi>(to wit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all reprofe of his ſinne and is of a braſen forhead as we ſay)</hi> but he that is iuſt wil direct his way. <hi>That is, he is not only willing to be admoniſhed, but of him ſelfe he is carefull to walke forward in good dutie. Cha.</hi> 21.29.</p>
                  <p>A wicked man is an abhomination to the iuſt, and he that is vpright in his way is an abhomination to the wicked. <hi>Chap.</hi> 29.27.</p>
                  <p>A wicked man taketh a gifte out of the boſome <hi>(that is, a gift which is ſecretlie and cloſely giuen)</hi> to wreſte the wayes of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.23.</p>
                  <p>A wicked meſſenger <hi>(that is, ſuch a one as dealeth vnfaithfully in that buſines wherwith he is betruſted)</hi> falleth into euill, but a very faithfull ambaſſador is preſeruation. <hi>Or as one that healeth or doth a greate cure and ſo is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to himſelfe in procuring the good of other. Chap.</hi> 13.17.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12612:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A wicked witneſſe mocketh at iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>(that is, he regardeth neither right nor wrong prophanely &amp; vnconſcionably abuſing the ſacred ſeate of iuſtice)</hi> yea ſo that the mouth of naughtie men ſwalloweth vp iniquitie <hi>(or thus)</hi> ſo doth iniquitie ſwallow <hi>(or ſoupe vp)</hi> the mouth of the wicked. <hi>That is al that they ſay or doe is greedely imployed in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice of ſinne:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But iudgementes are prepared for ſuch ſcorners, and ſtripes <hi>(that is, bruſing or bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering ſtripes)</hi> for the backes of ſuch fooles. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.28.29.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe heart <hi>(or the heart of a wiſe man)</hi> getteth knowledge <hi>(that is, he ſo getteth it that he holdeth it in poſſeſſion)</hi> and the eare of the wiſe ſeeketh learning, <hi>that is,</hi> continueth in ſeeking ſtill, to increaſe. <hi>Chapter,</hi> 18.15.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe King ſcattereth the wicked <hi>(or fanneth them)</hi> after that he hath cauſed the wheele to turne vpon them, <hi>(or as it were throſheth them) Chap.</hi> 20.26. <hi>That is, he vſeth all godlieſeueritie to the repreſſing or bettering of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A wiſe man concealeth knowledge <hi>(to wit, when it is no fit ſeaſon to vtter it)</hi> but the heart of fooles publiſheth <hi>(or proclaim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth)</hi> follie, <hi>that is, they doe it heartilie, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king pleaſure in it. Ch.</hi> 12.23.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe man feareth and departeth <hi>(that is,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12612:21"/>diuerteth or eſcapeth)</hi> from euill <hi>(or miſchiefe)</hi> but a foole bringeth himſelfe into trouble ſo confident <hi>(or ouer boulde and venterous</hi> is he. <hi>Chap</hi> 14 16.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe man goeth vp into the Citie of the mightie, and caſteth downe the ſtrength of the confidence thereof, <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.22.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe man is with ſtrength <hi>(or let a wiſe man be with ſtrength) that is, let him ioyne ſtrength with wiſdome and policie, as mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all helpers &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions)</hi> yea let a man of vnder ſtanding increaſe <hi>(or fortifie)</hi> ſtrength, <hi>that is, let him ad ſtrength to ſtrength. The reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</hi> For with wiſe councelles thou ſhalt proſperouſly make war &amp; by the multitud <hi>(or excellency)</hi> of counſellers <hi>thou ſhalt find ſafty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A wiſe reprouer <hi>(that is, he that repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth wiſely and with good diſcretion)</hi> is to the obedient eare as a goulden earing &amp; an orna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of fine gould. <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.12.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe ſon maketh a glad father, but a fooliſh ſonne is a heauineſſe to his mother, <hi>Ch.</hi> 10 1.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe ſon reioyceth the father, but a fooliſh ſonne deſpiſeth his mother, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.20.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe ſonne will obey the inſtruction of his father, but a ſcorner will heare no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.1.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe woman buildeth her houſe: but a fooliſh woman deſtroyeth it with her owne handes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.1, <hi>A verie vnnaturall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12612:22"/>and vnkinde part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A word ſpoken in his place <hi>(or in the right and currant manner as it ſhould be)</hi> is like apples of gould with pictures of ſiluer, <hi>Cha.</hi> 25.11.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>B</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>e diligent to know the ſtate <hi>(in heb: the</hi> faces) of thy cattell, <hi>(that is, or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſelfe in thine owne perſon)</hi> and take heede to the flockes,</p>
               <p>For riches remaine not alwayes: &amp; ſhall the crowne <hi>(continue)</hi> from generation to gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</p>
               <p>As ſoone as the heye diſcouereth it ſelfe, and the tender graſſe appeare, let the graſſe of the mountaines be gathered together.</p>
               <p>The lambes ſhalbe for thy clothing &amp; the goates for the price of a field <hi>that is, for the purchaſe of a fielde, to wit, through the plenti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full increaſe which they yeelde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>beſides there ſhall be</hi> ſufficiencie of the milke of the Goates for they foode, for the food of thy familie &amp; for the ſuſtena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c <hi>(or liuely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood)</hi> of thy maides. <hi>Ch.</hi> 27.23.24.25.26.27.</p>
               <p>Before dectruction the heart of a man is hautie, and before honour goeth lowlineſſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.12.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12612:22"/>
               <p>Behold the righteous, euen he is reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the earth, <hi>that is, he taſteth of GODS corrections for ſinne):</hi> howe much more the wicked and ſinner? <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.31,</p>
               <p>Be not thou a witneſſe againſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure without cauſe, <hi>(or vnaduiſedly)</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceiue him with thy lips: <hi>(or neither vndoe thou him with thy lippes:)</hi> Say not I will doe to him as he hath donne to me, I will recompence this fellowe according to his worke. <hi>Ch:</hi> 24.28.29.</p>
               <p>Be not thou enuious againſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>(or boiſterous)</hi> man, neither chooſe thou any of his waies:</p>
               <p>For the frowarde is an abhomination to the lorde: but his ſecret is with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The curſe of the Lorde is in the houſe of the wicked: but the habitation of the righteous is bleſſed.</p>
               <p>And inſomuch as he <hi>(that is God)</hi> ſcorneth the ſcornful but giueth grace to the humble: the wiſe ſhal inherit glorie, but reproch take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away fooles. <hi>Ch.</hi> 3.30.31.32, 33: 34.35.</p>
               <p>Be not thou enuious againſt euill men, neither deſire to be with them: for their heart imagineth deſtruction, and their lipes ſpeake miſchiefe. <hi>Ch:</hi> 24.1.2.</p>
               <p>Be not thou glad when thine enime fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, <hi>(I ſay againe)</hi> when he falleth let not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12612:23"/>thine owne hearte reioyce: Leſt the Lorde ſee it &amp; it diſpleaſe him, and he turne his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from him, <hi>to wit againſt thee. Chap:</hi> 24.17.18.</p>
               <p>Be not thou of them that touch the hand, nor of them that are ſuerties for debtes: If thou haſt nothing to pay why ſhoulde he <hi>(that is, the creditor, to wit, thoroughe thine owne defalte and raſhneſſe)</hi> take thy bed from vnder thee? <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.26.27.</p>
               <p>Be not thou wiſe in thine owne eyes, but feare the Lorde and departe from euill: So health ſhall be to thy nauell, and moiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>(or watering, that is, marrow,)</hi> to thy bones. <hi>His meaning is, by the reuerend feare of God thou ſhalt proſper in the boſome of the church through the ſecret bleſſing of God as the childe proſpereth after a wonderfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the wombe of the naturall mother. Ch:</hi> 3.7.8.</p>
               <p>Better is a drie morfell if peace be with it, then a houſe full of ſlaughtered <hi>beaſtes</hi> with ſtrife. <hi>Ch:</hi> 17.1.</p>
               <p>Better is a little with righteouſneſſe, then great reuenewes without equitie. <hi>Ch:</hi> 16.8.</p>
               <p>Better is a little with the feare of the Lorde, then greate treaſure and trouble therewith. Better is a dinner of greene hearbes where loue is, then a ſtalled oxe and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12612:23"/>hatred therewith. <hi>Ch:</hi> 15.16.17.</p>
               <p>Better is it to be of humble minde with the lowly, then to deuide the ſpoyle with the proude. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.19.</p>
               <p>Better is the poore that walketh in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie, then he that abuſeth his lippes and is a foole. <hi>Ch:</hi> 19.1.</p>
               <p>Better is the poore that walketh in his integritie, then he that peruerteth either of his waies <hi>(that is, declining either on the right hand or on the lefte)</hi> though he be rich. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28.6.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man that greatly feareth alwaies, <hi>(to vvitte, vvith ſuch a feare as doth not confounde or amaze him, but onelie cauſeth vvatchfulneſſe againſt ſinne vvith continuall prayer to God for the helpe of his grace):</hi> but he that hardeneth his hearte ſhall fall into euill. <hi>Ch:</hi> 28.14.</p>
               <p>Bleſſinges are vpon the heade of the righteous, but iniquitie <hi>(or violence)</hi> ſhall couer the mouth of the wicked. <hi>That is, his ovvne ſinne ſhall as it vvere ſmother and choake him. Ch:</hi> 10.6.</p>
               <p>Bloodie men hate him that is entier <hi>(that is him vvhoſe hearte is vvhollie in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of trueth vvith the lorde):</hi> but the iuſt haue care of his ſoule, <hi>(to vvit, to deliuer him from the malice of the cruell.) Chap.</hi> 29.10.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12612:24"/>
               <p>Boaſt not thy ſelfe before the King nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtand in the place of great men: <hi>(that is of noble perſonages):</hi> for it is better that it ſhoulde be ſaide to thee; come vp hether, then that thou ſhouldeſt be put lower in the preſence of him that is lowly minded whom thine eyes doe ſee <hi>(to vvit, to be prefered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch as preſume aboue their degree) or thus,</hi> which thing thine eyes doe ſee. <hi>Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the prowde man is debaſed to his ſhame. Ch:</hi> 25.6.7.</p>
               <p>Boaſt not thy ſelfe of to morrowe, for thou knoweſt not what the day may bring forth. <hi>Ch:</hi> 27.1.</p>
               <p>Buy the trueth but ſell it not; <hi>(euen the trueth,)</hi> of wiſedome and inſtruction and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. <hi>Ch:</hi> 23.23.</p>
               <p>By mercy and trueth <hi>(that is, through the mercie of God vvho is faithfull and true)</hi> iniquitie is forgiuen <hi>(or done avvay)</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the feare of the Lorde depart thou from euill. <hi>To vvit, as a dutifull childe loth to offende thy moſt gratious and heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Ch:</hi> 16.6.</p>
               <p>By the bleſſing of the righteous, <hi>(that is by the manifoulde good vvhich they procure by giuing councell, by doeing iuſtice, by main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Gods pure religion, and by their faithfull prayers to God)</hi> the citie is exalted: but it is ſubuerted by the mouth of the wicked. <hi>To
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12612:24"/>vvit, by their vvicked councell, by their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies &amp;c. Ch:</hi> 11.11. <hi>Read in S: Scornfull men &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>an a man take fire into his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, &amp; his clothes not be burnt? or can a mango vpon hote bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning coales <hi>(to wit, bare footed)</hi> and his feete not be burnte? So he that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into his neighbours wife, <hi>(to wit, with an adulterous minde)</hi> he ſhall not be innocent whoſoeuer toucheth her. <hi>Ch.</hi> 6.27.28.29.</p>
               <p>Caſt out the ſcorner, and ſtrife ſhall go out; and contention ceaſing, ſo ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo reproch. <hi>Ch:</hi> 22.10.</p>
               <p>Chaſten thy ſonne while there is hope, and let not thy ſoule ſpare for his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, <hi>or to his deſtruction.</hi> And if thou doe forgiue the puniſhment, yet ſhewe thy ſelfe verie angrie: for if thou letteſt him eſcape <hi>(to wit ouer remiſlie)</hi> thou muſt vſe more ſharpe correction afterwarde. <hi>Ch.</hi> 19.18.19.</p>
               <p>Childrens childen are the crowne of the elders: and fathers are the glorie of their children. <hi>Ch:</hi> 17.6.</p>
               <p>Committe thy workes vnto the Lorde, and they ſhall be directed together with thy thoughtes. <hi>Ch:</hi> 16.3. <hi>Reade. in T. The
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12612:25"/>preparations. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Confidence in an vnfaithfull man in time of trouble is like a broken tooth and a lame foote. <hi>(or a foote out of ioynt.) Ch:</hi> 25.19.</p>
               <p>Correct thy ſonne and he will cauſe thee to haue reſt, yea he will giue pleaſures to thy ſoule. <hi>Ch:</hi> 29.17.</p>
               <p>Councell in the hearte of man is like deepe waters: but a man that hath vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding will drawe it out. <hi>(To vvit, by vviſe queſtions and by taking advantage from all fit occaſions to prouoke him to ſhevve his opinion and iudgment. And marke that the vviſeſt men are deſcribed to be more ſparing in talke then the foole vvho vvill euer he ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blinge, Ch:</hi> 20.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>D</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eath and life are in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the tongue; as a man lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to vſe it, ſo ſhall he eate <hi>(that is, inioy)</hi> the fruite of it, <hi>Ch.</hi> 18.21.</p>
               <p>Debate with thy neighboure thy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which thou haſt againſt him, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer not an other mans ſecret:</p>
               <p>Leaſt he that heareth it put thee to ſhame, and leaſt thy diffamation <hi>(to wit, that euill reporte wherewith thou haſt diffamed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12612:25"/>thy neighbour)</hi> ceaſe not. <hi>So then he vſeth tvvo reaſons to perſvvade to the receiuing of the former precept according to the tvvo ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall partes of it. Ch:</hi> 25 9.10.</p>
               <p>Deceit <hi>(that is, fraudulent and deceitfull counſell)</hi> is againſt the heart of them that imagine <hi>(or plot)</hi> euill: <hi>that is, miſchife: (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we ſay commonly; euill counſell is worſt to the giuer:)</hi> but to the counſellers <hi>(that is, to the faithfull counſellers)</hi> of peace, ſhall be ioy. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.20.</p>
               <p>Depart from before the fooliſh man, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou perceiueſt not in him the wordes of knowledge. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.7.</p>
               <p>Diuers weightes and diuers meaſures, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen both theſe are abhomination to the Lord. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.10. <hi>And verſe.</hi> 23. Diuers weights are an abhomination to the Lord, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull ballances are not good.</p>
               <p>Doe not they erre that imagine <hi>(or buſie themſelues about)</hi> euill? <hi>(that is, about miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous practiſes)</hi> but to them that worke <hi>(or buſie themſelues in deuiſing &amp; practiſing)</hi> that which is good, ſhall be mercy and trueh. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.22.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>E</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Aſe ſtayeth the fooliſh, and the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of fooles deſtroyeth them. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.32.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12612:26"/>
               <p>Eate thou not the bread of him that hath an euill eie, neither deſire his daintie meates.</p>
               <p>For as if he thought it in his heart, ſo he wil ſay vnto thee; eate and drinke, but his heart is not with thee. <hi>Or thus.</hi> For as he thinketh <hi>(or eſteemeth)</hi> in his heart, ſo is he <hi>(or)</hi> ſo is it, <hi>(that is, ſo is he or his meat to be accounted of:)</hi> eate and drinke will he ſay; but his heart is not with thee: Thou ſhalt vomit thy morſel which thou haſt eaten: <hi>(that is, thou ſhalt haue no ioy but ſhalt find thy ſtomack as it were ouerlaid at ſuch a mans table, though thou take but a ſmall pittance: to wit, if thou followe not this counſell to abſtaine altogether from it:)</hi> and thou ſhalt looſe all thy pleaſant wordes. <hi>(That is, all thy wordes of welcome. (Or)</hi> when thou haſt loſt <hi>(or caſt it vp) (that is, when thou ſhalt finde thy ſelfe nothing beholding to him, no not for one morſell of his meate or one draught of his drinke)</hi> thy affaires <hi>(or buſineſſe which thou goeſt about)</hi> ſhall be more ioyous <hi>(or delight full) vnto thee. Ch.</hi> 23.6.7.8.</p>
               <p>Enter not into the way of the wicked, neyther walke thou in the way of euil men.</p>
               <p>Auoyde it, and goe not by it; turne from it, and paſſe by.</p>
               <p>For they cannot ſleepe vnleſſe they haue done euill, and their ſleepe is taken from them if they haue not cauſed ſome to fall:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12612:26"/>For they eate the bread of wickedneſſe, and drinke the wine of all kinde of violence. <hi>(That is, whatſoeuer they can get by hooke, or by crooke as we ſay.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the way of the righteous, is as the light which ſhineth, yea which goeth on in ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>(or ſhineth more and more)</hi> vnto the perfect day <hi>(that is, to high noone) or thus,</hi> which goeth on in ſhining, ſo as <hi>euery one of them</hi> is firme in day, <hi>(that is, conſtantly continuing and abiding in the light of the day, walking as it were in the light of the Lord vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly and in the plaine path. &amp;c.)</hi> As for the way of the wicked it is like the darkeneſſe, they know not whereat they ſhall ſtumble. <hi>or ſall. Chap.</hi> 4.14.15.16.17.18.19.</p>
               <p>Eſtabliſh thoughtes by counſell, and by counſell make warre. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.18.</p>
               <p>Euen a foole when he holdeth his peace <hi>(that is, auoideth raſhnes)</hi> is counted wiſe, and when he ſtoppeth his lippes prudent. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28.2. <hi>Read in H. He that hath knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Euen by laughter <hi>(that is, by wicked mirth or earnall iolitie)</hi> the heart is ſorrowfull: and the end of that mirth is heauineſſe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.13.</p>
               <p>Euerie waye of man is right in his owne eyes: but the Lorde pondereth the heartes. <hi>Chap:</hi> 21.2.</p>
               <p>Euerie wiſe man dealeth by knowledge <hi>(that is, he will not be buſie in ſuch thinges as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12612:27"/>he is ignorant in)</hi> but a foole ſpreadeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, <hi>(or layeth open)</hi> follie. <hi>To wit, by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling in matters aboue his skill. Chap.</hi> 13.16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>F</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aire words <hi>(or pleaſant and delightfull ſpeeches, to wit, ſuch as are fit for the vſe of edification)</hi> are ſweetneſſe to the ſoule and cauſing health to the bones. <hi>That is, they are as good phiſicke, and verie medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Chap.</hi> 16.24.</p>
               <p>Falſe ballances are an abhomination to the Lord, but a perfect weight pleaſeth him. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.1.</p>
               <p>Fooliſhneſſe is bound in the hart of a child, but the rod of correction wil remoue it farre away from him. <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.15.</p>
               <p>Fooliſhneſſe is ioy to him that is without hart <hi>that is, to ſuch a one as is deſtitute of vnder ſtading</hi>) but a man which hath vnderſtanding will walke vprightly. <hi>Yea he will make this his ioy. Chap.</hi> 15.21.</p>
               <p>For the deſire thereof <hi>(or to the end he may haue his deſire)</hi> he will ſeparate himſelfe to ſeeke it, and occupy himſelfe in all wiſedom <hi>(or, in euery weighty matter, or in all thinges that are.) Reade in A. A ſciſmaticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 18.1. <hi>Reade alſo the next verſe. A foole hath no delight. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:12612:27"/>
               <p>For the tranſgreſſion of a land there are manie Princes thereof <hi>(that is, there are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten channges)</hi> but by a man of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and knowledge a realme likewiſe indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth long: <hi>or rather thus;</hi> but when a man is wiſe and skilfull, <hi>(to wit, in the godlie gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his realme)</hi> he doth by that meanes prolong it. <hi>(To wit, his reigne or gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.) Chap.</hi> 28.2.</p>
               <p>Frette not thy ſelfe becauſe of the maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, neither be enuious at the wicked: For there ſhall be no ende to the euill man, <hi>(that is, no good and happie ende)</hi> the light of the wicked ſhall be put out. <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.19.20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>G</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>O not forth haſtely to ſtrife <hi>(or to ſute it at lawe)</hi> leaſt that which thou wouldeſt doe, <hi>(vnto him)</hi> doe in the ende, <hi>fall vpon thy ſelfe;</hi> when thy neighbor hath put thee to ſhame. <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.8. <hi>And then it followeth in the next verſe.</hi> Debate with thy neighbour &amp;c. <hi>Reade in D.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God ouerthroweth the wicked that they are not: but the houſe of the righteous ſhall ſtande. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Or thus.</hi> The wicked ouerthrowe themſelues, &amp;c. <hi>To wit, by their prouoking of GOD by their ſinnes to their owne deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12612:28"/>
               <p>Good vnderſtanding maketh acceptable, but the way of the diſobedient is hated. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.15. <hi>Or thus,</hi> Grace, <hi>(that is, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious or dutifull behauiour, through the grace and mercie of God)</hi> giueth good ſucceſſe, but the way of the diſobedient is roughe. <hi>That is to ſay, it is not proſperous. Reade in T. Thornes &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Go to the Piſmire <hi>(or ant)</hi> ô ſluggard: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlde her wayes, and be wiſe.</p>
               <p>Albeit ſhe haue no guide, gouernour, nor ruler:</p>
               <p>She prepareth her meate in ſummer, and gathereth her meate in harueſt.</p>
               <p>How long wilt thou lie ô ſluggard? when wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleepe? Yet a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſleepe a little ſlumber <hi>(or a fewe ſhorte ſleepes, a fewe ſhorte ſlumbers, to wit, as the ſluggard deemeth them though they might a bundantly ſuffice)</hi> a little fowlding of the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to ſleepe, <hi>or to lie ſtill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore thy pouertie commeth as a right <hi>(or ſpeedie)</hi> traueler, and thy neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie like an armed man. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.6.7.8.9.10.11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>H</head>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12612:28"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>atred ſtirreth vp contentions <hi>(to wit, ſuch as are accompanied with tauntinges and reuilinges &amp;c.)</hi> but loue couereth all treſpaſſes. <hi>That is, it will not reproue ſinne after that manner, but with pittie and compaſſion and in all holie diſcretion, Chap.</hi> 10.12.</p>
               <p>He alſo that is ſlouthfull <hi>(or negligent and remiſſe)</hi> in his worke, is euen a brother to him that is a greate waſter <hi>(or ſtroy-good) Chap.</hi> 18.9.</p>
               <p>Heare counſell and receiue inſtruction that thou maiſt be wiſe at the latter ende, <hi>Ch.</hi> 19.20.</p>
               <p>Heauines in the heart of man doth bring it down: but a good word reioyceth it. <hi>(or a good, that is to ſay, a proſperous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter)</hi> reioyceth it. <hi>To wit, the hand of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, whereof reade in the verſe before. See in T. The hand &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 12.24.25.</p>
               <p>Hell and diſtruction are before the Lord: <hi>that is, he knoweth them throughly and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a ſoueraigne power ouer them:</hi> how much more the heartes of the ſonnes of men? <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.11.</p>
               <p>He loueth tranſgreſſion that loueth ſtrife: and he that ſeeketh to make breache <hi>(or diuiſion)</hi> inlargeth the gate thereof. <hi>That is, of all kinde of tranſgreſſion. Chapter</hi> 17 19.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:12612:29"/>
               <p>He ſhall before vexed that is ſuertie for a ſtranger: but he that hateth ſuch as doe ſtrike handes, <hi>(to wit, raſhly)</hi> is fure. <hi>Or without feare, to wit, of the creditor, Chap.</hi> 11, 15.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that A</head>
                  <p>HE that anſwereth a matter before he heare it <hi>(that is, before he doe aduiſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare and conſider of it)</hi> it is a follie and ſhame vnto him. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that B</head>
                  <p>HE that begetteth a foole <hi>(begetteth him)</hi> to his owne ſorrow: neither ſhal the father of a foole haue any ioy. <hi>That is, he ſhall haue no true cauſe of ioy in him ſo long as he continueth in his follie, that is, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly. Chap.</hi> 17.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that C</head>
                  <p>HE that cauſeth the righteous to go a ſtray by an euill way, ſhall fall into his owne pit: but the entier <hi>(or perfect, that is, they that continue in the ſtraight wayes of the Lord)</hi> ſhall inherit good thinges, <hi>Cha.</hi> 28.10</p>
                  <p>He that couereth a tranſgreſſion ſeeketh loue, but he that repeateth a matter, <hi>(that is, which reuiueth a matter of reproch, in his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12612:29"/>anger which before lay deade and was forgotten,)</hi> ſeparateth a chiefe friende. <hi>That is, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienateth his minde and affection from him. Chap.</hi> 17.9.</p>
                  <p>He that curſeth his father or his mother, his light ſhall be put out in obſcure dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.20.</p>
                  <p>He that delicatly bringeth vp his ſeruant from his youth, at length he will be euen as his ſonne. <hi>That is, he will grow ouer bold and ſaucie, forgetting himſelfe to be a ſeruant, and he will proue contemptuous and iniurious againſt his maiſters children. Chapter,</hi> 29.21.</p>
                  <p>He that deſpiſeth the word ſhal be diſtroied, but he that feareth, <hi>(that is, reuerently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth)</hi> the commaundement, ſhall be rewarded. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.13.</p>
                  <p>He that deſtroyeth hisfather or chaſeth away his mother is a lewde and ſhamefull childe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.26. <hi>Or as followeth.</hi> A childe which cauſeth ſhame and reproch conſumeth his father <hi>(that is, his fathers goods)</hi> &amp; cauſeth his mother to fly from him.</p>
                  <p>He that diggeth a pit ſhall fall therein, &amp; he that rowleth a ſtone it ſhall returne vpon him <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.28.</p>
                  <p>He that diſſembleth hatred with lying wordes, and he that inuenteth <hi>(or brocheth)</hi> a ſlander is a foole, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:12612:30"/>
                  <head>He that F</head>
                  <p>HE that findeth a wife findeth a good thing, &amp; receiueth fauour of the Lord. <hi>(or thus)</hi> and that fauour which is from the Lord hath promoted him. <hi>Chapter,</hi> 18.22.</p>
                  <p>He that followeth after righteouſneſſe and mercie, ſhall finde life, righteouſneſſe and glorie. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that G</head>
                  <p>HE that gathereth in ſommer is a wiſe ſonne, but he that ſleepeth much in harueſt is a ſonne of confuſion <hi>(or)</hi> a ſon that maketh aſhamed. <hi>To wit, himſelfe and thoſe that depend vpon him, through his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouident follie. Chap.</hi> 10.5.</p>
                  <p>He that giueth to the poore ſhall not lacke, but he that hideth his eyes <hi>(that is, he that will not tender the miſeries of the poore)</hi> ſhall haue manie curſes. <hi>To wit, not only from men by imprecationes, but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from God as the auenger of the vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, Chap.</hi> 28.27.</p>
                  <p>He that goeth about as a ſlaunderer <hi>(or a talecarier &amp; backbiter)</hi> diſcouereth a ſecret but he that is of a faithfull heart concealeth a matter. <hi>To wit, euerie ſuch matter as ought in good dutie to be concealed. Chap.</hi> 11.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:12612:30"/>
                  <head>He that H</head>
                  <p>HE that hateth will counterferte with his lippes, but in his inwarde part <hi>(that is, in his heart)</hi> he layeth vp <hi>(or plotteth)</hi> deceit.</p>
                  <p>Though he ſpeake fauorablie truſt him not, for there are ſeauen abhominations in his heart.</p>
                  <p>Hatred maybe couered by deceite, but the malice thereof ſhall be diſcouered in the congregation. <hi>Ch.</hi> 26.24.25.26.</p>
                  <p>He that hath a good eye ſhal be bleſſed: for he giueth of his breade to the poore. <hi>Ch:</hi> 22.9.</p>
                  <p>He that hath knowledge in deede <hi>(or knoweth knowledge, that is, howe it ſhoulde be vſed)</hi> ſpareth his wordes: for a man of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is of an excellent <hi>(or of a coole and temperat)</hi> ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Yea euen a foole when he holdeth his peace is counted wiſe, and when he ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his lippes prudent. <hi>Ch.</hi> 17.27.28.</p>
                  <p>He that hath mercy on the poore lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto the lorde: and he will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence vnto him that which he hath giuen. <hi>Ch.</hi> 19.17.</p>
                  <p>He that hideth his ſinnes ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper: but he that confeſſeth and forſaketh them ſhall haue mercy. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that I</head>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:12612:31"/>
                  <p>HE that increaſeth his riches by vſurie and intereſt gathereth them for him that will be mercifull to the poore. <hi>Chap.</hi> 28.8.</p>
                  <p>He that is deſpiſed, and hath a ſeruant of of his owne, <hi>(or is his owne ſeruant)</hi> is better then he that boaſteth him ſelfe, and lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth breade. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.9.</p>
                  <p>He that is deſtitute of wiſdome <hi>(or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth hearte)</hi> deſpiſeth his neighbour: but a man of much vnderſtanding <hi>(that is, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſcreete man)</hi> will keepe ſilence. <hi>That is, he will not doo as the other doeth, Chapter.</hi> 11.12.</p>
                  <p>He that is firſt in his owne cauſe <hi>(that is, the plantine) ſeemeth to be iuſt:</hi> but when his neighbour, <hi>(that is, the defendant)</hi> commeth, he <hi>(that is, the iudge)</hi> trieth him. <hi>Ch.</hi> 18.17. <hi>A notable deſcription of a right courſe of proceeding to iudgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that is greedy of gaine troubleth his ovvne houſe, but he that hateth giftes ſhall liue. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.27. <hi>To witte a bleſſed life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that is haſty to anger commiteth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and a buſie body is hated. <hi>(or thus)</hi> therefore to a prudent man it, <hi>(that is, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineſſe to anger)</hi> ſhall be odious <hi>or hatefull. Ch.</hi> 14.17.</p>
                  <p>He that is mercifull rewardeth his owne ſoule, but a cruell man troubleth his owne
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12612:31"/>fleſhe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.17. <hi>Reade alſo the next two verſes in T. The wicked worketh &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that is of a large hearte <hi>(that is, he that is prowde and licentious)</hi> will make much ſtrife; but he that truſteth in the Lorde ſhall be fatte. <hi>that is, he ſhall proſper, Ch.</hi> 28.25.</p>
                  <p>He that is partener with a thiefe hateth his owne ſoule <hi>yea and</hi> he that heareth cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge <hi>(that is, any execrable and notorious wickedneſſe)</hi> and declareth it not. <hi>Ch.</hi> 29.24. <hi>So farre ought euerie man to be from ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or conſenting with the wicked in any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie practiſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that is flowe to anger is better then the mighty man, and he that ruleth ouer his minde, then he that winneth a citie. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.32.</p>
                  <p>He that is flow to wrath is of great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: but he that is of a haſtie ſpirite exalteth <hi>(or lifteth vp)</hi> folly. <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.29.</p>
                  <p>He that is wiſe in his buſineſſe, <hi>(or thus)</hi> he that attendeth to the word ſhall finde <hi>(that is, atteine to)</hi> good, and bleſſed is he that truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Lorde. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.20.</p>
                  <p>He that iuſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the iuſt, they are both a like abhomination to the Lorde. <hi>Ch.</hi> 17.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that K</head>
                  <p>HE that keepeth his mouth and his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12612:32"/>tongue keepeth his ſoule from afflictions. <hi>Ch.</hi> 21.23.</p>
                  <p>He that keepeth his mouth keepeth his life, but he that proſtituteth his lippes, it ſhall be deſtruction to him. <hi>Ch.</hi> 13.3.</p>
                  <p>He that keepeth the commaundement keepeth his ſoule: but he that deſpiſeth his waies <hi>(that is, the wayes of God)</hi> ſhall die. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.19.</p>
                  <p>He that keepeth the figge tree ſhall eate the fruite thereof: ſo he that waiteth vpon his maiſter ſhall come to honour. <hi>Chapter.</hi> 27.18.</p>
                  <p>He that keepeth the lawe is a prudent ſonne: but he that feedeth, <hi>(or is acompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with)</hi> gluttons, ſhameth his father. <hi>Chap</hi> 28.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that L</head>
                  <p>HE that loueth his ſoule poſſeſſeth his heart, he keepeth vnderſtanding that he may finde goodneſſe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 19.8.</p>
                  <p>He that loueth inſtruction loueth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: but he that hateth correction is a foole. <hi>(or brutiſh). Ch.</hi> 12.1.</p>
                  <p>He that loueth paſtime <hi>(or iolitie)</hi> ſhall be a poore man: &amp; he that loueth wine and oile, <hi>(that is, he that is ouer deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and dainty)</hi> ſhall not be rich. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.17.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:12612:32"/>
                  <p>He that loueth pureneſſe of heart: for the grace of his lippes, the kinge ſhall be his friende. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that M</head>
                  <p>HE that mocketh the poore reprocheth him that made him ſo: <hi>(that is, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth the Lord God who maketh either poore or rich whom it pleaſeth him)</hi> and he that reioyceth at deſtruction ſhall not be vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <hi>Ch.</hi> 17.5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that O</head>
                  <p>HE that oppreſſeth the poore reprocheth him that made him: but he that hath mercie on the poore honoureth him. <hi>That is to ſaye God, who maketh whom he will poore, as before. Ch.</hi> 14.31.</p>
                  <p>He that oppreſſeth the poore to increaſe himſelfe, and he that giueth to the rich ſhal ſuerly come to pouertie. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that P</head>
                  <p>HE that paſſeth by, and angrilie medleth with the ſtrife that belongeth not vnto him, is as one that taketh a dogge by the eares. <hi>Ch.</hi> 26.17.</p>
                  <p>He that praiſeth his friende with a loude voice riſing earlie in the morning, it ſhall be counted to him as a curſe. <hi>(That is, it
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12612:33"/>ſhall not be accepted. A iuſt rewarde of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious flatterie. Ch.</hi> 27.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that R</head>
                  <p>HEe that rebuketh a man ſhall finde more fauoure at the length, <hi>or as Trem:</hi> He that rebuketh a man after me <hi>(that is, to cauſe him towalke in the wayes of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inſtructions of K. Salomon)</hi> he ſhall finde more fauoure then he that flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth with his tongue. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28.22.</p>
                  <p>He that regardeth inſtruction is in the way of life: but he that refuſeth correction cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to go out of the waie. <hi>Or thus:</hi> The way of life is his that regardeth inſtruction: but the way of him that refuſeth correction couſeth to erre. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10.7.</p>
                  <p>He that reproueth the wiſe and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent eare is as a golden earing and an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of fine golde. <hi>Ch.</hi> 25.12. <hi>Reade in A. A wiſe reprouer &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that rewardeth euill for good, euill ſhall not depart from his houſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.13.</p>
                  <p>He that robbeth his father and mother, and ſayeth it is no tranſgreſſion, is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of a man that deſtroyeth. <hi>(That is, he that waſteth his fathers goods and mocketh at all admonition is worthy to haue like puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the murtherer according as his ſinne
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12612:33"/>is of like nature. Ch,</hi> 28. <hi>See Deut.</hi> 24.21.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that S</head>
                  <p>HE that ſaith to the wicked, thou art righteous, him ſhall the people curſe, multitudes ſhall abhorre him. But to them that rebuke him ſhall be pleaſure, and vpon them ſhall come the bleſſing of goodneſſe <hi>(or of the goood man:</hi> He <hi>(that is to ſay, the good and godly man)</hi> will kiſſe the lippes of him that anſwereth vpright wordes. <hi>That is, he will greatlie reuerence ſuch a one. Chap.</hi> 24.24.25.26.</p>
                  <p>He that ſeeketh carneſtly <hi>(to doe)</hi> good getteth fauour: but he that ſeeketh euill <hi>(or as touching him that ſeeketh euill, that is, to worke miſchiefe)</hi> it ſhall come vnto him. <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.27.</p>
                  <p>He that ſendeth a meſſage by the hande, <hi>(that is, by the miniſterie and ſe ruice)</hi> of a foole, doth as if he ſhould cut off the feete <hi>(to wit, of the meſſenger after that he hath commaunded him his ſeruice)</hi> and ſo drinke the fruite of crueltie. <hi>For it were better and more ſafe, (ſpecially in matters of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) not to ſend at all, then to ſende a foole, whether he be ignorant, or hauing meete know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, be knowne to be vnfaithfull. Chap.</hi> 26.6.</p>
                  <p>He that ſoweth iniquity ſhall reape affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and by therod of his owne anger he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12612:34"/>ſhall falle. <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.8.</p>
                  <p>He that ſpareth his rod hateth his childe, but he that loueth him nourtureth him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.24.</p>
                  <p>He that ſpeaketh trueth will ſhew righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: but a falſe witneſſe vſeth deceit. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.17. <hi>Or thus.</hi> He that ſheweth that which is right ſpeaketh the trueth: <hi>(this doth a very faithfull witneſſe, he regardeth not onely what is true, but alſo what is meete to be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon as Ier.</hi> 4.2.) but a witneſſe of falſhoodes <hi>(that is, an arrant falſe witneſſe, ſuch a one as we cal a knight of the poſt, who hath ſet his faith to ſale)</hi> vttereth deceit. <hi>That is, he doth for aduantage ſake either diſguiſe at his pleaſure or vtterly falſifie or denie the trueth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that T</head>
                  <p>HE that taketh away the garment in the cold ſeaſon is like vineger <hi>poured</hi> vpon nitre, or like him that ſingeth ſongs to a heauy hearte. <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.20. <hi>(Or as Trem. according to the, vſuall ſignification of the firſt word of the ſence noe, and as all things ſeeme moſt aptly to agree thus.</hi> As he that putteh on a garment in the cold ſeaſon, or vineger vpon niter, ſo is he that ſingeth ſonges to a troubled mind. <hi>That is, he comforteth the heauy hart, as the garment cauſeth warmth to the cold body, and as vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reſolueth niter &amp; maketh it fit for vſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12612:34"/>for ſcouring or any other ſeruice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that tilleth his land ſhal be ſatisfied with bread; but he that followeth after vaine thinges, <hi>(That is, which spendeth his time vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftily)</hi> is deſtitute of vnderſtanding. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.11. <hi>And Chap.</hi> 28.19. he ſhall be filled with pouerty.</p>
                  <p>He that troubleth his owne houſe ſhall inherite the winde: and the foole ſhall be ſeruant to the wiſe in heart. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.29.</p>
                  <p>He that truſteth in his own heart is a foole, but he that walketh in wiſedome <hi>(that is, he that walketh in the feare of God &amp; maketh him his ſtay)</hi> ſhalbe deliuered. <hi>Chap.</hi> 28.26.</p>
                  <p>He that turneth away his eare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hearing the law, euen his praier is abhominable. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>He that VV</head>
                  <p>HE that walketh on forward in his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity is righteous: and bleſſed ſhall his children be after him. <hi>Or thus.</hi> The righteous man walketh on forward in his integrity, and bleſſed, &amp;c. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.7.</p>
                  <p>He that walketh on in his righteouſneſſe feareth the Lord: but he that is lewde in his waies deſpiſeth him. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.2.</p>
                  <p>He that walketh vprightly <hi>(or entierly)</hi> ſhalbe ſaued: but he that is ſtoward in either of his waies, <hi>(to wit, either on the right hand or on the left; eyther in exceſſe or in defect, that is, in any
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12612:35"/>extreeme wickedneſſe)</hi> ſhall once fall. <hi>(Or)</hi> fall in one of them. <hi>Chap.</hi> 28.18.</p>
                  <p>He that walketh vprightly <hi>(or entirely, as before)</hi> walketh boldly, but he that peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his waies, ſhall be knowne. <hi>(Or made an example. To wit, by ſome iudgement of God that other may learne to beware. Chap.</hi> 10.9 <hi>as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth verſe</hi> 10. <hi>He that winketh, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that walketh with the wiſe ſhal be wiſe; but he that is a companion with fooles ſhall be afflicted, <hi>(or rather) will waxe worſe. Chap.</hi> 13.20.</p>
                  <p>He that winketh with the eye, <hi>(that is, the cloſe diſſembler)</hi> who worketh ſorrow, &amp; the fooliſh in talke ſhalbe beaten. <hi>Or,</hi> ſhall bring trouble vpon himſelfe. <hi>(That is, both the one and the other ſhall be puniſhed. Chap.</hi> 10.10.</p>
                  <p>He that withdraweth corne, <hi>(or)</hi> As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that withdraweth corne, the people will curſe him: but bleſſing ſhall be vpon the head of him that ſetteth it forth to ſel. <hi>C.</hi> 11.26</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>H I</head>
                  <p>HIgh talke <hi>(or excellent ſpeech)</hi> be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not a foole, <hi>(that is, to vtter it) (or)</hi> is nothing pleaſant to a foole, <hi>(to wit, when he beaneth it from the mouth of an other:)</hi> much leſſe lying talke <hi>(is pleaſing)</hi> to him that is wel diſpoſed. <hi>(Or beſemeth)</hi> a Prince, <hi>or chief man. Chap.</hi> 7.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:12612:35"/>
                  <head>H O</head>
                  <p>HOnour the Lord with thy riches, and with the firſt fruits <hi>(or chiefe)</hi> of all thine increaſe. So ſhall thy barnes be filled with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance and thy preſſes ſhal guſh out with new wine. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.9.10.</p>
                  <p>Houſe and riches are inheritance from fathers <hi>(or anceſtors)</hi> but a prudent wife com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the Lord. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.14.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a wiſe man contend, <hi>(or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the matter)</hi> with a fooliſh man, whether he be angry or laugh, yet there is no reſt. <hi>Cha.</hi> 29.9. <hi>as Luke.</hi> 7.31. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If he that hateth thee be hungry, giue him bread to eat, &amp; if he be thirſty giue him water to drink: For thou ſhalt <hi>(as it were)</hi> heape coles vpon his head, <hi>(that is, thou ſhalt this way beſt winne his loue if he wil be gained, or execute the beſt reuenge in leauing him to the iudgement of God, if he will continue his malice)</hi> and the Lorde will recompence thee. <hi>To witte, all which thou maiſt ſeeme to haue caſt away vpon thine enemie. Chap.</hi> 25.21.22.</p>
               <p>If thou be faint in the day of aduerſity, thy ſtrength is ſmall. <hi>Or after an other pointing of the ſentence thus.</hi> If thou behaue thy ſelfe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12612:36"/>faintly <hi>(or remiſly &amp; negligently,)</hi> thy ſtrength ſhall be ſmall <hi>(or ſtreighted)</hi> in the time of ſtreightneſſe. <hi>Or aduerſitie.</hi> Deliuer them that are drawen to death; <hi>(that is, ſuch as are vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently and not by due courſe of iuſtice haled to death)</hi> for wilt thou withdrawe thy ſelfe from ſuch as are going aſide to death <hi>(or ſlaughter?)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou ſay, behould, we knew it not: ſhall not he that pondereth the heartes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand? and he that keepeth thy ſoule, <hi>ſhall not he</hi> know? and <hi>will not he alſo</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence euerie man according to his workes? <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.10.11.12. <hi>A precept to thoſe that haue lawful power in their hande to reſcue the oppreſſed: and alſo to ſuch as be in fauour with chiefe magiſtrates that they do ſolicite theire cauſe: finally to euerie one of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes of God that they mutually helpe one an other againſt the iniuries of the wicked and vngodly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou haue founde honie eat that which is ſufficient for thee, leaſt beeing full of it thou doe vomit it:</p>
               <p>So make thy foote pretious <hi>(to wit, by withdrawing it)</hi> from thy neighbours houſe, leaſt he be glutted with thee and hate thee. <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.16.17.</p>
               <p>In all labour there is abundance <hi>(or ſom profit ariſing by it)</hi> but when the lippes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly talke, <hi>all goeth</hi> to wracke, <hi>Chapter</hi> 14.23.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:12612:36"/>
               <p>Incline thine eare and heare the wordes of the wiſe, and apply thine heart vnto my knowledge:</p>
               <p>For it ſhall be a pleaſant thing, if thou keepe theſe thinges in thy bellie, and if they be directed together in thy lippes: If thy confidence ſhall be in the Lord; and if al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>thou wilt doe that</hi> which I haue this day made knowen vnto thee.</p>
               <p>Haue I not written to the excellent things <hi>(or moſt princely ſayings) conſiſting</hi> in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels and knowledge;</p>
               <p>Making knowne vnto thee that which is certaine, euen the wordes of truth, that thou maiſt anſwere with wordes of truth to them that ſhall ſend vnto thee? &amp;c. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.17.18.19.20.21.</p>
               <p>In many wordes <hi>(or)</hi> By a multitude of wordes, <hi>(that is, though he that is faltie vſe neuer ſo manie wordes to excuſe himſelfe)</hi> iniquitie ceaſeth not: <hi>(that is, the faulte is neuer the leſſe for that)</hi> therefore he that is wiſe refraineth his lippes. <hi>To witte, as one being content to take a rebuke when his falt is laide open before him. Ch.</hi> 10.19.</p>
               <p>Inſtruction is euill to him that forſaketh the way, <hi>(that is, he accounteth it euill, he cannot like of it no more then the rogue or vagabond perſon liketh to be directed to goe to the place where he ſhould be, to follow the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12612:37"/>duties of ſome honeſt calling)</hi> and he that hateth correction ſhall die. <hi>Chapter</hi> 15.10.</p>
               <p>Intende <hi>(or practiſe)</hi> not any hurt <hi>(or miſchieuous deuice)</hi> againſt thy neighboure who dwelleth without feare by thee.</p>
               <p>Striue not with any man cauſeles, when he hath donne thee no harme, <hi>Chapter,</hi> 3.29.30.</p>
               <p>In the feare of the Lord there is an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ſtrength, <hi>(or a ſtrong aſſurance,)</hi> and his children ſhall haue hope. <hi>Or rather thus,</hi> for he will be to his children as a place of reſkue. <hi>Or ſuccour. Ch.</hi> 14.26.</p>
               <p>In the houſe of the wiſe man there is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie deſirable <hi>(that is verie pretious)</hi> treaſure and oyle: but a fooliſh man deuoureth it. <hi>Ch.</hi> 21.20.</p>
               <p>In the light of the Kings countenance is life, and his fauour is as a full cloude of the latter raine. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.15.</p>
               <p>In the lippes of him that hath vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſdom is found: but the rod muſt be at the backe of him that wanteth hearte. <hi>That is, of him that is deſtitute of wiſdome Chap.</hi> 10.13.</p>
               <p>In the mouth of the fooliſh man is the rod of pride, <hi>(that is, ſuch proude and naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſpeaches which are as a rod to cauſe him ſelfe to be beaton with all)</hi> but the lippes of wiſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12612:37"/>men doe preſerue them. <hi>To wit, themſelues from puniſhment through their wiſe ordering of their ſpeaches. Ch.</hi> 14.3.</p>
               <p>In the multitude of people is the honour of the king; but for want of people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the deſtruction of the prince. <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.28.</p>
               <p>In the proſperitie of the righteous <hi>(that is, when they proſper or when it goeth well with them)</hi> the citie reioyceth <hi>(to wit, all godly minded Citizens)</hi> Yea with ſhouting) <hi>or ſinging do they reioyce)</hi> when the wicked periſh. <hi>to wit, whether by the ordinarie vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation and hand of God or by anie extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie iudgement. For it goeth well with the ſheepe when the Wolfe is worried &amp;c. Chapt.</hi> 11.10.</p>
               <p>In the tranſgreſſion of a man is an euill ſnare, but the righteous doe ſing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce. <hi>To wit, as hauing the libertie and peace of a good conſcience. Ch.</hi> 29.6.</p>
               <p>In the tranſgreſſion of the lipps is the ſnare of a wicked man, but the iuſt ſhall come out of aduerſitie <hi>Ch.</hi> 12.13.</p>
               <p>Ioy commeth to a man by the anſwere of his mouth: and ô how good is a worde <hi>(or a thing)</hi> in his due ſeaſon. <hi>Ch</hi> 15.23.</p>
               <p>I paſſed by the field of the ſlouthfull man, and by the vinyarde of the man deſtitute of heart <hi>(that is, of vnderſtanding.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And behold it was all growen ouer with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12612:38"/>thiſtles: and nettles had couered the face thereof, and the ſtone-wall thereof was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken dowen.</p>
               <p>Then I beheld, I conſidered it well, <hi>I</hi> loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon it, I receiued inſtruction.</p>
               <p>Yet a little ſleepe, a litle ſlumber <hi>(or thus)</hi> By a fewe ſhorte ſleepes, by a few ſhort ſlu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, by a little whiles fowlding of the hands to lye downe <hi>(or) in playing the ſlug ſtill,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>(or in the meane while)</hi> thy pouertie commeth as a ſpeedie traueller <hi>(or wayfaring man)</hi> and thy neceſſitie like an armed man, <hi>(to wit to take the ſluggard vnarmed and in his naked bed ſo as there can be no reſiſting) Chapter,</hi> 24.30.31.32.33.34. <hi>Reade in G. Goe to the piſmire &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a mans honour to ceaſe from ſtrife, but euerie foole will be meddling, <hi>(or) wil make himſelfe buſines. Chap.</hi> 20.3.</p>
               <p>It is an abhomination for Kinges to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit wickedneſſe: for the throne is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by iuſtice. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.12.</p>
               <p>It is a paſtime to a foole to doe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly: but wiſdome to a man of vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that is, it is his delight to exerciſe or practiſe that which is according to true wiſdome. Ch.</hi> 10.23.</p>
               <p>It is a ſnare to a man <hi>(to wit, ſuch a ſnare at will intrap him to deſtruction)</hi> to deuoure
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12612:38"/>that which is ſanctified and after vowes to inquire <hi>(to wit, with a minde to elude or call them backe againe. Ch.</hi> 20.25.</p>
               <p>It is better for a man to meet a beare, robbed of her whelpes, then a foole in his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. <hi>Or thus, as the wordes will well beare.</hi> Let a man meete a ſhee beare robbed of her whelpes, and not a foole in his follie. <hi>(That is, while he is in his rage.) As though he ſhould ſay: this were more perillous and vnauoidable then that. Ch.</hi> 17.12.</p>
               <p>It is better to dwell in a corner of the houſe roofe <hi>(to witte, of the flatte roofe as the people of Iſraell vſed to builde)</hi> then with a contentious woman in a wide houſe. <hi>(Or)</hi> in a houſe of ſocietie. <hi>That is, fitte and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious for man and wife to dwell comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably therein.</hi> Ch. 21.9. <hi>And the ſame againe. Ch.</hi> 25.24.</p>
               <p>It is better to dwell in the wilderneſſe then with a contentious and angrie woman. <hi>Ch.</hi> 21.19.</p>
               <p>It is ioy to the iuſt to doe iudgment; but it is a deſtruction <hi>(or as one woulde ſaye, it is a death)</hi> to the workers of iniquitie. <hi>To wit to doo that which is equall and right. That is to ſay, they vtterlie abhorre and ſhun it. Ch.</hi> 21.15. <hi>Read in E. Enter not &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is naught, it is naught, <hi>(that is, it is verie naught, the worſt that euer I handled
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12612:39"/>&amp;c.)</hi> ſaieth the buier: but when he is gone a part, he boaſteth himſelfe. <hi>To wit, of his good penniworth; how like ye my bargaine ſayeth he, haue I not hucked well &amp;c. Here therefore is the falt: the correction of it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is gold <hi>(ſaieth K: S:)</hi> and plentie of pretious ſtones <hi>(to wit, in the handes of the buyer and ſeller)</hi> but the lippes of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge are the moſt pretious iewell. <hi>(or the inſtrument and implement or merchandiſe of greateſt price) to witte, when as men haue a conſcionable regard of that which they ſpeake both in buying and ſelling, and in all other their contracting and dealing one with an other Ch.</hi> 20.14.15.</p>
               <p>It is not good to accept the perſon of the wicked, to cauſe the righteous to fall in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Ch.</hi> 18.5.</p>
               <p>It is not good to eate ouermuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, neither is it any glory <hi>for men</hi> to ſearch after their owne glorie, <hi>Ch:</hi> 25.27.</p>
               <p>Iudgments are prepared for ſcorners, and ſtripes for the backe of fooles, <hi>Ch.</hi> 19.29. <hi>Readin A. A wicked witneſſe &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iuſtice exalteth a nation: but ſinne is a ſhame <hi>(or reproch)</hi> to any nation. <hi>Or people. Ch.</hi> 14.34.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>K</head>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:12612:39"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Eepe thine hearte with all diligence: for thereout commeth life. <hi>Ch.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Read in A. Aboue. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>L</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ay no waite ô wicked man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the houſe of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; ſpoyle thou not his reſting place. For be it that a iuſt man fall ſeuen times yet he riſeth againe: <hi>(to wit, by the holy helpe and hande of God)</hi> but the wicked they fall together <hi>(or all at once) in their miſchiefe. That is, God caſteth them downe by an irrecouerable and deadly downfall. Ch.</hi> 24.15.16.</p>
               <p>Let an other man praiſe thee and not thine owne mouth: a ſtranger and not thine owne lippes. <hi>Ch.</hi> 27.2.</p>
               <p>Life is in the way of righteouſneſſe, and in that path way is no death. <hi>That is, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie and euerlaſting deliuerance from death and from all feare of death is there to be founde. Who therfore ſhoulde not be effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moued to enter that path and to walke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in it? Ch.</hi> 12.28.</p>
               <p>Loue not ſleepe, leſt thou come to pouertie; open thin eyes, <hi>(that is, be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in following the duties of thy calling) and ſo be thou</hi> ſatiſfied with breade. <hi>Or, thou ſhalt be ſatiſfied with bread. Ch.</hi> 20.13.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:12612:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:12612:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:12612:41"/>
               <head>M</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ake no frendſhip with an angrie man, neither go thou with the furious man: Leaſt thou learne his waies, and receaue deſtruction <hi>(or a ſnare)</hi> to thy ſoule. <hi>That is, ſuch a ſnare as ſhoulde indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thy ſoule to the heauie diſpleaſure of God, Ch.</hi> 22.24.25.</p>
               <p>Many deuices are in mans heart: but the councell of the Lorde it ſhall ſtand. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.21.</p>
               <p>Many doo ſeeke the face of the ruler: but euerie mans iudgment, <hi>commeth,</hi> from the Lorde. <hi>Ch.</hi> 29.26.</p>
               <p>Many men, <hi>(or thus)</hi> As touching the multitude <hi>(or greater parte of men)</hi> euerie one maketh boaſt of his goodneſſe: but who can finde a man of faithfulneſſe? <hi>That is to ſay, a man that is verie faithful indeed. Ch.</hi> 20.6.</p>
               <p>Many reuerence the face of the Prince. <hi>Or thus;</hi> Many make ſute to the prince: <hi>(or to him that is francke and liberally min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:)</hi> and euerie man is friende to him that giueth giftes. <hi>Or, that is bountifull,</hi> Ch. 19.6. <hi>But it is contrariwiſe with the poore man who is caſt off on all handes, as it followeth in the next verſe. Read in A. All the brethren &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:12612:41"/>
               <p>Mercy and trueth: <hi>Or we may reade thus:</hi> Clemency and faithfulnes preſerue the kinge, and he eſtabliſheth his throne by clemencie. <hi>Or mercie. Ch.</hi> 20.28.</p>
               <p>Much foode is in the fielde of the poore: but the fielde is deſtroyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcretion. <hi>Or as followeth.</hi> Much foode commeth to the poore by tillage: but there is that conſumeth himſelfe through neglect of his duetie. <hi>He meaneth euen ſome of ſuch as haue (as we ſpeake) much to take to, Ch.</hi> 13.23.</p>
               <p>My ſonne, be wiſe and reioice my heart that I may anſwere him that woulde reproch me in any matter. <hi>Ch.</hi> 27.11. <hi>Marke here how notably the good bringing vp of children plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for the credit and eſtimation of Parents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My ſonne, eate hony for it is good, and the hony combe which is ſweete to the roofe of thy mouth: So know that wiſdome wil be to thy ſoule if thou ſhalt finde it; for there ſhall be a rewarde and thy hope ſhall not be cutte off. <hi>Ch.</hi> 24.13.14.</p>
               <p>My ſonne, feare the Lorde and the Kinge, and haue no fellowſhippe with them that are ſeditious <hi>(or looſe and licentious)</hi> for their deſtruction ſhall riſe vp ſodainlie; and who knoweth the ruine of them both? <hi>That is, both of the inordinate and licentious them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and alſo of thoſe that ſhall ſorte and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12612:42"/>company with them. Ch.</hi> 24.21.22.</p>
               <p>My ſonne, giue me thy heart, and let thine eyes delight in <hi>(or heedefully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue)</hi> my waies: For a whore is as a deepe ditch, <hi>and a ſtrange woman (that is, ſuch a one as eſtrangeth her ſelfe from the holy waies of God: as Chap.</hi> 2.16.17.) Is as a narrowe pit. Alſo ſhe lieth in wait as for a pray, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth tranſgreſſours among men.</p>
               <p>To whome is woe? To whome is alaſſe? <hi>(or ſorrow.)</hi> To whome is much ſtrife? To whom is babling? To whom are woundes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe? <hi>(that is, euen ſuch as he may thanke no bodie for but himſelfe)</hi> to whom is the red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the eies? Euen to them that tary long at the wine; to them that goe and ſeeke after mixt wine.</p>
               <p>Looke thou not vpon the wine when it waxeth red, and vttereth his colour in the cuppe, and goeth downe pleaſantly <hi>(or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus)</hi> and moueth it ſelfe <hi>(or ſparteleth and springeth, to wit, in the cup)</hi> as being of the right <hi>(or beſt)</hi> kinde.</p>
               <p>In the ende thereof, it will bite like a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſting like a cookatrice <hi>(or viper.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thine eies wil looke vpon ſtrange women, and thine heart will ſpeake lewde thinges.</p>
               <p>And thou ſhalt be as one that lyeth in the middeſt of the ſea, yea as one that lyeth in the toppe of the maſt. <hi>That is, greatly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12612:42"/>reeling and ſtaggering too and fro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They haue ſtricken me <hi>(wilt thou ſay)</hi> but I was not ſicke, they haue beaten <hi>(or pummeled)</hi> me, but I felt it not: when <hi>(therefore)</hi> I ſhall awake, <hi>(to wit, as one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſlept away the former drunkenneſſe)</hi> I will to it againe, I will ſeeke it yet more. <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.26.27.28.29.30.31.32.33.34.35. <hi>A liuely deſcription of the beaſtly vnſatiable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; miſerable condition of the drunken man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My ſonne, heare thy fathers inſtruction, and forſake not thy mothers teaching: for they ſhal be a comely ornament to thy head and as chaines for thy necke. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.8.9.</p>
               <p>My ſonne, hearken vnto my wordes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine eares to my ſayings.</p>
               <p>Let not them <hi>(that is, the vvicked, to wit, by any perſwaſions of theirs to the contrary)</hi> cauſe that they <hi>(to vvit, my wordes)</hi> ſhould depart from thine eies, but keepe them in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of thy heart.</p>
               <p>For they are life vnto thoſe that find them, and healthfull to the whole fleſh of euery of them.</p>
               <p>Aboue euery watch watch ouer <hi>(or keepe)</hi> thine heart, for from it are the outgoings <hi>(or iſſues, that is. the actions)</hi> of life.</p>
               <p>Put away from thee a froward mouth, and remooue wicked lippes farre from thee. Let thine eies behold the right <hi>(or look right forth)</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:12612:43"/>and let thine eie-lids looke directly before thee.</p>
               <p>Ponder the path of thy foote, yea let all thy waies be ordered aright: <hi>(or vvell ſette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſtayed:)</hi> Turn not to the right hand nor to the left, but remoue thy foote from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. <hi>That is, from euery by-path of ſinne. Ch.</hi> 4. <hi>verſes.</hi> 20.21.22.23.24.25.26.27.</p>
               <p>My ſonne, if ſinners intiſe thee conſent thou not. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.10. &amp;c. <hi>And verſes</hi> 15.16. My ſonne walke thou not in the way with them, refraine thy foote from their path: For with their feete they runne to euill, and they make haſt to ſhed blood, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>My ſonne, if thine heart be wiſe, my heart ſhall reioyce, and I alſo; <hi>(that is, I ſhall whollie or throughly reioyce, euen I that am thy father.)</hi> yea my reines ſhall reioyce, when thy lippes ſpeake righteous thinges.</p>
               <p>Let not thy heart be enuious againſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: but <hi>let it be</hi> in the feare of the Lorde continually: <hi>Or,</hi> let it imitate thoſe that are conſtant in the feare of the Lorde: For ſurely there is a reward, and thy hope ſhall not be cut off. <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.15.16.17.18.</p>
               <p>My ſonne, if thou be ſurety for thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>(or friend)</hi> and haſt ſtricken hand with a ſtranger, Thou haſt ſnared thy ſelfe with the words of thy mouth, thou art taken with the words of thine owne mouth. <hi>(To witte
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12612:43"/>as it were in the net of the fouler, or in the trap of the hunter.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doe this nowe ô my ſonne, and deliuer thy ſelfe, ſeeing thou art come into the hande of thy neighbour: <hi>(To wit, of him for whome thou art become ſuertie, for whome, and by tendering of whoſe credit, thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered thine owne ſelfe, and ſtandeſt bound to pay the debt if he neglect to doe it:)</hi> Goe thou, humble <hi>(or ſubmit)</hi> thy ſelfe, <hi>(to wit, vnto the creditor, that if neede be thou maieſt finde him fauourable)</hi> and earneſtly ſolicite, <hi>(or doe thou mightilie importune)</hi> thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>(that is, him for whom thou art ſuretie, to witte, leaſt he breake day, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Giue no ſleepe to thine eies, nor ſlumber to thine eie-lids.</p>
               <p>Deliuer thy ſelfe as a roe <hi>(that is, as a ſwift deare)</hi> from the hand of the hunter, <hi>(to wit, as one all readie taken by the heele)</hi> and as a birde from the hande of the fowler. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.1.2.3.4.5.</p>
               <p>My ſonne, beare no more the inſtruction. that cauſeth to erre from the wordes of knowledge. <hi>Or as followeth.</hi> Leaue off <hi>(or ceaſe)</hi> my ſonne, to erre from the wordes of knowledge, to the end thou maiſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to inſtruction. <hi>That is, that thou maieſt be a true and profitable ſcholler in the ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of God; which poſſiblie cannot be till
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12612:44"/>thou renounce the vanitie of thine owne errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vvaies. Chap.</hi> 19.27.</p>
               <p>My ſonne deſpiſe not the chaſtening of the Lord, neither be thou grieued at his corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Or let it not be tedious vnto thee, that is, anoide eyther extremitie, and labour to make a good and holie vſe of euerie viſitation, bleſſing the Lord in them. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Lord correcteth him whome he loueth, euen as a father doth the childe in whome he delighteth. <hi>Or, to whom he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well. Chap.</hi> 3.11.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>N</head>
               <head>O</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F a Prince that hearkeneth to lies, all his ſeruants are wicked. <hi>Chap.</hi> 29.12.</p>
               <p>O howe much better is it to get wiſedome then gold; and to get vnderſtanding <hi>(ô how much more)</hi> to be deſired aboue ſiluer! <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.16.</p>
               <p>Onely by pride doth man make conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but with the well aduiſed is wiſedom. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.10.</p>
               <p>Open rebuke is better then ſecrete <hi>(or concealed and hidden)</hi> loue. <hi>That is, ſuch loue as is idle, and faileth in the neceſſarie dnetie of it.</hi> The woundes <hi>(that is, the moſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12612:44"/>ſharpe rebukes)</hi> of a louer <hi>(that is, of a louing friend, ſuch a one as loueth indeed)</hi> are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: but the kiſſes of an enemy <hi>(or of him that hateth, though he pretend friendſhip)</hi> are to be praied againſt. <hi>(Or, to be had in execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on how pleaſant or fauning ſoeuer they be. Ch.</hi> 27.5.6.</p>
               <p>O thou my ſonne, heare and be wiſe; and let thine heart goe this way. <hi>(To vvit, vvhich I ſhall novv ſhevv thee.)</hi> Keepe not company with thoſe that be drunken with wine, nor with thoſe that glut themſelues with meate: For the drunkard &amp; the glutton ſhalbe poore and drowſineſſe <hi>(to vvit, that vvhich follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and accompanieth drunkenneſſe and glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie)</hi> clotheth with ragges. <hi>That is, maketh ſuch as take that courſe, to goe in ragged coats.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obey thy father that hath begotten thee, and deſpiſe not thy mother when ſhe ſhall be olde.</p>
               <p>Buy the trueth but ſell it not; <hi>euen the trueth</hi> of wiſedome and inſtruction and vnderſtanding. <hi>Or in this ſenſe. Buy all theſe and ſell none of them but keepe them by thee as iewels for euer to be knowen by.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The father of the righteous ſhall greatlie reioyce, and he that begetteth a wiſe childe, <hi>(that is, ſuch a child as in time imbraceth the holie vviſedome and feare of God)</hi> hath ioy of him. <hi>(VVherefore thou for thy parte,)</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:12612:45"/>
               <p>Let thy father reioyce, and thy mother: <hi>(to wit, for thy wiſdom and godlineſſe which they ſhall perceiue in thee:)</hi> yea let her that bare thee reioyce. <hi>Ch.</hi> 23. <hi>verſe.</hi> 19.20.21.22.23.24.25.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>P</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Leaſure is not comelie for a foole, much deſſe that a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant ſhould beare rule ouer princes. <hi>That is, it is not meet that ſuch a one ſhould beare rule who ſtandeth in more neede to be ruled himſelfe Chap.</hi> 19.10.</p>
               <p>Pouertie and ſhame <hi>(or reproch)</hi> ſhall be to him that refuſeth <hi>(or withdraweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from)</hi> inſtruction: but he that regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>(that is, which continuoth in regarding or obſeruing correction, to wit, ſo as he will ende his life thereafter)</hi> ſhall be honored. <hi>Ch.</hi> 13.18.</p>
               <p>Prepare thy worke without, and make readie thy thinges in the fielde, <hi>(or thus)</hi> and get that for thy vſe <hi>(or commoditie)</hi> which is in the fielde <hi>(that is, doe the moſt neceſſarie thinges firſt)</hi> and after alſo thou ſhalt builde thy houſe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 24.27.</p>
               <p>Pride goeth before deſtruction, and an high minde before the fall. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.18.</p>
               <p>Proude, hautie, and ſcornfull is his name,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12612:45"/>who in his wrath worketh arrogancie. <hi>That is, who carieth himſelfe proudely in his anger. Ch.</hi> 21.24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Q</head>
               <head>R</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emoue not the aunciente boundes, neither enter thou into the fields of the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: <hi>to wit, with a minde to diſpoſeſſe them of their right:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For their redeemer <hi>(or a uenger)</hi> is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he will pleade their cauſe againſt thee. <hi>Ch.</hi> 23.10.11.</p>
               <p>Riches auaile not in the day of wrath: <hi>(that is, when God ſhall enter into iudgment with the wicked rich man)</hi> but righteouſnes deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth from death. <hi>That is, they that loue and practiſe righteouſneſſe in the obedience of the true iuſtifying faith, finde fauour with God, and ſhall eſcape from death to life Chapt.</hi> 11.4.</p>
               <p>Riches gather many friendes, but the poor man is ſeparated from his neighbour, <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.4. <hi>and verſe.</hi> 6. <hi>Reade in M. Manie reuerence &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Righteous lippes are the delight of Kings <hi>(to wit, of good Kings, and when they be affecte
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12612:46"/>as they ought to be)</hi> and he <hi>(that is, the good King)</hi> loueth him that ſpeaketh right things. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.13.</p>
               <p>Righteouſneſſe preſerueth him that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire <hi>(or ſound and vpright)</hi> in the way: but wickednes ouerthroweth the man of ſinne. <hi>that is, ſuch a one as hath giuen him ſelfe vp to ſinne. Ch.</hi> 13.6.</p>
               <p>Rob not the poore becauſe he is poore, <hi>(as though he ſhould ſay, let euen his pouertie be as letters of protection to ſafe conduct him from all iniurious dealing)</hi> neither oppreſſe the afflicted, in the gate, <hi>(that is, in the place of iudgement and vnder colour of law:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Lord will pleade their cauſe, and ſpoyle the ſoule of thoſe that ſpoile them: <hi>that is, he will vtterlie ſpoyle them. Chap.</hi> 22.22.23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>S</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aye not, I will recompence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, but waite vpon the Lord, &amp; he will ſaue thee <hi>Ch.</hi> 20.22.</p>
               <p>Scornefull men bring the citie into a ſnare, <hi>(or)</hi> ſet it on fire. <hi>Towit, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bellows of contention</hi>) but wiſe men <hi>(to wit, ſuch as haue wiſe regard of common peace and tranquilitte)</hi> turne away wrath <hi>That is, they meet with &amp; preuent ſeditions &amp;c. Ch,</hi> 26.8.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:12612:46"/>
               <p>Seeſt thou a man diligent in his buſines? He ſhall ſtand before kinges, he ſhall not ſtand before the baſe ſorte. <hi>Chapter</hi> 22.29.</p>
               <p>Seeſt thou a man haſtie in his wordes <hi>(or matters and buſineſſe,)</hi> there is more hope of a foole then of him. <hi>Ch.</hi> 29.20.</p>
               <p>Seeſt thou a man wiſe in his own eyes <hi>(that is, in his owne conceite, ſtanding as it were in his owne light as we ſay,)</hi> there is more hope of a foole then of him, <hi>Ch.</hi> 26.12.</p>
               <p>Slouthfulnes cauſeth deepe ſleepe to fall vpon a man <hi>(whereby commeth want)</hi> and the deceitfull perſon ſhall be hungry. <hi>Or afa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed. That is, one puniſhment ſhall be for both theſe ſinnes, as vſualle meeting in one &amp; the ſame perſon Ch.</hi> 19.15.</p>
               <p>Smite a ſcorner, and the foliſh <hi>(or ſimple)</hi> man will be made warie: and by reprouing him that is prudent, he <hi>(that is, the ſimple man)</hi> will vnderſtand knowledge. <hi>The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is that either way the ſimple man will be holpen notwithſtanding he be of meete capacitie. Chapter.</hi> 19.25. <hi>Reade againe in W. When the ſcorner &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Speake not in the eare of a foole, for he will deſpiſe thee with the wiſdome of thy ſayings, <hi>Ch.</hi> 23.9.</p>
               <p>Surely it is not good to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n the iuſt, nor that princes ſhould ſmite ſuch for equity. <hi>Or thus in an other conſtruction.</hi> neither is it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12612:47"/>to ſmite ſuch as are well diſpoſed. <hi>Ch.</hi> 17.26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>T</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake his garment that is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erty for a ſtranger &amp; a pledge of him that is <hi>ſuerty</hi> for ſtrange woman, <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.16. <hi>And againe Chapter</hi> 27.13. <hi>The meaning is, that God permitteth that ſuchas will be ſo raſhe, and fooliſh (notwithſtanding his admomtion to the contraris) that they ſhould paye well for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take away the droſſe from the ſiluer, and there ſhall proceede a veſſell for the finer. <hi>Or thus.</hi> As by taking away &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So by talding a way the wicked from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, his thorne ſhall he eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in righteouſnes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.4.5.</p>
               <p>Teach <hi>(or as we may reade it)</hi> Catechiſe a childe in the trade of his way<hi> (or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that courſe of life which be is to enter into, That is, how he is to walk in good dut is both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God and man in the faith and obedience of the Goſpel)</hi> &amp; euen when he ſhall be olde he will not departe from is. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.6. <hi>A notable and moſt gratious incouragement for all chriſtian Parentes to bringe vp their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren euen from their yonge yeares in the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12612:47"/>and information of the Lorde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which is to be deſired of a man is his goodneſſe, <hi>Or thus:</hi> That which a man ought chiefely to deſire, is his goodnes: <hi>(that is, that he may be kinde and bountifull, then the which nothing beſeemeth a man more):</hi> but a poore man is better then a liare <hi>Chapter.</hi> 19 22.</p>
               <p>That which the wicked feareth ſhall come vpon him: but God will graunt the deſire of the righteous. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10.24. <hi>The next verſe may be a further expoſition of this. Read in A. As the whirlwinde. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The B</head>
                  <p>THe beginning of ſtrife is as one that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth the waters: therefore ere the contention be meddeled with, leaue off. <hi>Or thus.</hi> He that is the beginninge of ſtrife, is as one that openeth a paſſage for the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>(to wit, of ſuch as are dammed or banked vp)</hi> wherefore ere it breake forth <hi>(or spread it ſelfe)</hi> leaue off the contention. <hi>Chapter.</hi> 17.14.</p>
                  <p>The beutie <hi>(or ornament)</hi> of yonge men is their ſtrength, <hi>(or valoure)</hi> and the glorie of the aged is the gray heade. <hi>(Or thus)</hi> and the grayneſſe <hi>(or whiteneſſe)</hi> of the haire is a ſeemely <hi>(or reuerende)</hi> gracing to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. <hi>Ch.</hi> 20.29.</p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:12612:48"/>
                  <p>The bleſſinge of the Lorde it maketh rich, and he doth adde no ſorrowe with it. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10.22.</p>
                  <p>The blewneſſe <hi>(to wit, of the fleſh)</hi> and the wounde <hi>(or ſtroke that fetcheth bloode)</hi> yea ſtripes that <hi>peirce</hi> to the bowelles of the bellie <hi>(that is, which make the hearte akeas we ſay)</hi> ſerue to purge <hi>(or are the inſtrumentes for the purging, that is, for the curing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of)</hi> the euill man. <hi>He meaenth ſuch a one as we call ſtarke naught or a verie bad one. And thus we may ſee how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie ſeueritie is allowed and commended of God. Ch.</hi> 20.30.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The C</head>
                  <p>THe crowne of the wiſe is their riches, but the fooliſhneſſe of fooles is foliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>To wit, ſtill: that is, fooles are neuer the wiſer though they be rich, and therefore their riches is no crowne or ornament but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a reproch vnto them, ſeeing, hauing rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es they neither knowe nor regarde to vſe them well, but are vaſſals vnto them. Chap</hi> 14.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The D</head>
                  <p>THe deceitfull man ſhall not roſt that which he hath taken in hunting: he that is diligent <hi>(inioyeth)</hi> the pretious riches <hi>(or
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12612:48"/>wealth)</hi> of man. <hi>Ch.</hi> 12.27.</p>
                  <p>The deſire of the righteous is onely good <hi>(that is prosperous)</hi> but the hope of the wicked is indignation. <hi>That is, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they hope for good, that falleth out which grieueth and vexeth them as a iuſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment from the wrath and indignation of God. Ch.</hi> 11.23.</p>
                  <p>The deſire of the ſlouthfull ſlaieth him, in ſo much as his handes refuſe to worke.</p>
                  <p>He euermore coueteth, gredilie; but the righteous giueth and ſpareth not. <hi>Or withholdeth not. To wit, his handes either from giuing according to his abilitie, or from diligence in his honeſt laboure. Chapter.</hi> 21.25.26.</p>
                  <p>The diſcretion of a man cauſeth him to defer his anger <hi>(or maketh him longe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering)</hi> and it is his glorie to paſſe by an offence. <hi>Ch.</hi> 19.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The E</head>
                  <p>THe eare that harkeneth to the correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life, ſhall remaine among the wiſe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15 31.</p>
                  <p>The euill man is ſnared by the wickednes of his lippes, but the iuſt ſhall come out of aduerſitie. <hi>Or thus,</hi> In the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the lippes is the ſnare of an euill man <hi>&amp;c. as before. Ch:</hi> 12.13.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:12612:49"/>
                  <p>The euill ſhall bowe <hi>(or in the preſent tenſe, doo bowe)</hi> themſelues before the good, and the wicked at the gates of the righteouſſe. <hi>This doth God of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie bring to paſſe manie times, howe contrarie ſo euer it be to the liking of the wicked. Ch.</hi> 14.19.</p>
                  <p>The eyes of the Lorde are in euerie place beholding the euill and the good. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.3.</p>
                  <p>The eyes of the Lorde preſerue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>(that is, he preſerueth all ſuch as haue carewiſely to vnderſtand, and to doo the vvill of God)</hi> but he ouerthroweth the wordes of the tranſgreſſor. <hi>That is, whatſoeuer he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh, according to the follie of his owne heart. Ch.</hi> 22.12.</p>
                  <p>The excellent that formed all things both rewardeth the foole, and alſo rewardeth tranſgreſſors. <hi>Ch:</hi> 26.10. <hi>A ſentence of greate difficultie from the varietie of the hebrewe conſtruction. Read in A. As a throne &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The F</head>
                  <p>THe feare of man layeth a ſnare <hi>(that is, his owne feare is a ſnare to himſelfe)</hi> but he that truſteth in the Lorde ſhalbe exalted. <hi>(That is, he ſhal be lifted vp and ſet as it were on a high place out of daunger. Ch.</hi> 29.25.</p>
                  <p>The feare <hi>(or rather)</hi> The terror of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12612:49"/>Kinge is like the roring of a yonge Lion <hi>(that is, it is moſt fierce and terible)</hi> he againſt whom he is angrie, ſinneth againſt his owne ſoule, <hi>(that is, he putteth himſelfe in the perill of his life by provoking him) Ch.</hi> 20.2.</p>
                  <p>The feare of the Lorde increaſeth the daies: but the yeares of the wicked ſhall be diminiſhed. <hi>Ch:</hi> 10.27.</p>
                  <p>The feare of the Lorde is a well ſpringe of life to avoide the ſnares of death. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.17.</p>
                  <p>The feare of the Lord is the beginning <hi>(or as the worde alſo ſignifieth, the excellency &amp; chiefetie)</hi> of knowledg, but fooles deſpiſe wiſedome and inſtruction. <hi>Ch.</hi> 1.7.</p>
                  <p>The feare of the Lorde is the inſtruction of wiſedome and before honour goeth hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.33. <hi>Or rather thus,</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of wiſdome <hi>goeth before</hi> the feare of the Lorde, and humilitie before honour. <hi>But how then may it be ſaid as in the ſentence next before, that the feare of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge. Anſwere. Inſtruction is the meanes and inſtrument to giue wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but knowledge is not heartily imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vntill God by his holy Spirit, doth, worke a reuerend regard of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The feare of the Lorde <hi>tendeth</hi> to life <hi>(or is for the maintenance and nouriſhment of life that is to ſay, of spirituall life:)</hi> he that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12612:50"/>is once ſatiſfied <hi>therewith</hi> ſhall contine we <hi>ſo,</hi> neither ſhall he be viſited with euill. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.23.</p>
                  <p>The fining pott <hi>is</hi> for ſiluer <hi>(that is, for the trying and fining of ſluer)</hi> and the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace for golde, yea euerie thing according to his dignitie <hi>(or anſwerable to that vſe for the which it is prayſed) But</hi> though thou ſhouldeſt bray a foole in a morter amonge wheat brayed <hi>(or as betweene the mil or querne ſtones)</hi> with a peſtell, yet would not his foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe depart from him. <hi>Chap.</hi> 27.21.22. <hi>Behold therefore how deeply &amp; ſtrongly naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe is ſetled in our corrupt nature which can not by any meanes be beaten out but by the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie grace of the ſpirit of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fooliſh doe inherite follie <hi>(that is, they hold is &amp; reioyce in it as in an inheritance)</hi> but prudent men make knowledge their crown. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.18.</p>
                  <p>The fooliſh make a mocke of ſinne) <hi>or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as followeth)</hi> Sinne <hi>(or giltines of ſinne)</hi> is a meane to ſet fooles at one <hi>(or to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a fooles paradice as one would ſay,)</hi> but among the righteous, that which is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, <hi>to wit, that which God alloweth, worketh content and agrement among them, Chap.</hi> 14.9.</p>
                  <p>The fooliſh man wil beleue euerything, but the prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t man will conſider his ſteps, <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.15.</p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:12612:50"/>
                  <p>The fooliſhneſſe of a man peruerteth his way and his heart fretteth againſt the Lord. <hi>Reade in A. As well. &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 19.3.</p>
                  <p>The froward in heart findeth <hi>(or attaineth to)</hi> no good thing: and he that hath a naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie tongue <hi>(or is guilefull and craftie in his tongue, that is, he who hath a glibbe tongue to carie matters this way and that way to ſerue his owne turne)</hi> he ſhall fall in euill. <hi>Ch.</hi> 17.20.</p>
                  <p>The fruite of the righteous is the fruit of the tree of life, and he that winneth ſoules is wiſe. <hi>Or thus.</hi> For he being wiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth ſoules. <hi>To vvit, in the way of life and ſaluation. Chap.</hi> 11.30.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The G</head>
                  <p>THe gathering of treaſure, <hi>(vvorde for worde, the vvorke of treaſures, that is, about the gathering of treaſure,)</hi> by a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tongue, is as vanity toſſed <hi>(or driuen)</hi> to and fro: they ſeeke death. <hi>To wit, which ſeeke riches ſo. Chap.</hi> 21.6.</p>
                  <p>The glorie of God is to hide a thing, but it is the honor of kinges to ſearch out a matter. The heauens in height and the earth in deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; the heart of kings ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſearched out. <hi>(Or there is no ſearching out of them.) Ch.</hi> 25.2.3. <hi>The firſt of thoſe prouerbes which the men of</hi> Hezekiah <hi>king of Iuda copied out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The good man ſhal giue <hi>(or deliuer ouer)</hi> his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12612:51"/>inheritance to childres children <hi>(that is, God wilſo bleſſe his poſterity.)</hi> And the riches of the ſinner are laid vp for the righteous. <hi>C.</hi> 13.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The H</head>
                  <p>THe hand of the diligent ſhal beare rule, but the idle <hi>(or deceitfull hand)</hi> ſhalbe vnder tribute. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.24.</p>
                  <p>The heart knoweth the bitterneſſe of the owne ſoule, <hi>(that is, of it ſelfe)</hi> and no ſtrange thing ſhall intermingle it ſelfe with the ioye thereof. <hi>That is, as enery man is affected ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvell or ill, ſo he liketh or diſliketh, keepeth or ſhunneth company, &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 14.10. <hi>Reade the</hi> 9. <hi>verſe. The fooliſh make a mocke of ſinne &amp;c. This ſeemeth to render a reaſon of that.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The heart of him that hath vnderſtanding ſeeketh knowledge <hi>(that is, it continueth in ſeeking)</hi> but the mouth of ſooles is fed with fooliſhmeſſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.14.</p>
                  <p>The heart of man purpoſeth his waie: but the Lord doth direct <hi>(or order and diſpoſe)</hi> his ſteppes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.9.</p>
                  <p>The heart of the righteous ſtudieth <hi>(or meditateth)</hi> what to ſpeake, but the mouth of wicked men belcheth out <hi>(that is, rudely and raſhly babbleth out)</hi> euill things. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.28.</p>
                  <p>The heart of a wiſe man guideth his mouth wiſely and he addeth <hi>(or furthereth)</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by his lippes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.23.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:12612:51"/>
                  <p>The hart that is declined <hi>(or he whoſe heart is turned backe)</hi> ſhalbe ſatiate with the own waies, but a good man <hi>(will depart)</hi> from him. <hi>That is, he wil be ſhie of his company. Ch.</hi> 14.14.</p>
                  <p>The hope that is deferred maketh the heart to faint; but when the deſire <hi>(that is, the thing deſired)</hi> commeth, it is as a tree of life. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.12.</p>
                  <p>The houſe of the righteous hath much treaſure <hi>(or ſtrength: that is, it is firmely eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed)</hi> but by the reuenewes of the wicked man, his houſe is diſturbed. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.6.</p>
                  <p>The houſe of the wicked ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but the tabernacle of the righteous ſhall flouriſh. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The I</head>
                  <p>THe inſtruction of a wiſe man is as a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of life to turne away, <hi>(that is, it teacheth vs to turne away or depart from)</hi> the ſnares of death. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The K</head>
                  <p>Hhe kings heart is in the hand of the lord as the riuers of water, he turneth it whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoeuer it pleaſeth him. <hi>That is, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it ſaile as it were a ſtil flowing ſtreame to ſtrue his owne moſt holy purpoſe &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell in all thinges. Chap.</hi> 21.1.</p>
                  <p>The kings wrath, is like the roaring of a yong Lyon, but his fauour is like the dew vpon the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12612:52"/>graſſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The L</head>
                  <p>THe labor of the righteous tendeth to life, <hi>(that is, to the neceſſary &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable main tenance of life in the feare of God)</hi> but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenews of the wicked to ſin. <hi>That is, they are conſumed to ſerue their wicked luſts. Ch.</hi> 10.16. The liberal perſon <hi>(in heb. The ſoule of bleſſing that is, he that is hartily beneficial)</hi> ſhal haue plenty <hi>(in Heb. ſhall be fat. i. ſhall proſper)</hi> and he that watereth abundantly ſhal poure forth the more. <hi>In Heb ſhall caſt forth, that is, God vvill bleſſe him with ſuch increaſe that he ſhall be able ſo to doe. Chap.</hi> 11.25.</p>
                  <p>The light of the eies reioyceth the heart, and good hearing <hi>(that is, the hearing of good things)</hi> maketh the bones fatte. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.30. <hi>Reade the next verſe. in T. The eare. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The light of the Lord is the ſoule of man: <hi>Or rather thus.</hi> The ſoule of man is as a light <hi>(or candle)</hi> of the Lord <hi>(that is, which the Lord hath lighted and ſet vp in him)</hi> wherewith he <hi>(that is to ſay man)</hi> ſearcheth all the bowels of the bellie. <hi>That is, by the light of his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he findeth out verie ſecret thinges. Chap.</hi> 20.27. <hi>This may be more particularly referred to the king of whome we reade in the</hi> 16. <hi>verſe next before. Reade in A. A. wiſe King. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:12612:52"/>
                  <p>The light of the righteous ſhall reioyce, <hi>(that is, it shall be bright; their proſperity and happineſſe shall be glorious)</hi> but the candle of the wicked ſhalbe put out. <hi>That is, all their pompe shall vaniſh &amp; come to nothing. Ch.</hi> 13.9.</p>
                  <p>The lippe of trueth <hi>(that is, vvhich ſpeaketh the trueth)</hi> is eſtabliſhed for euer, but a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tongue indureth but a moment. <hi>Or while I might neuer ſo little mooue my foote. Or in the turning of a hand. &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 12.19.</p>
                  <p>The lips of the righteous doe feed many: but fooles ſhall die for want of wiſedome. <hi>In Heb. Forwant of heart. Chap.</hi> 10.21.</p>
                  <p>The lippes of the righteous doe knowe <hi>(or regard)</hi> that which is acceptable: <hi>(and conſequently they find fauour)</hi> but the mouth of the wicked ſpeaketh froward things. <hi>Euen ſuch as procure their own ouerthrow. Ch.</hi> 10.32.</p>
                  <p>The lippes of the wiſe do ſpread abroad knowledge: but the heart of the fooliſh that which is not right. <hi>That is, they ſet their minds to ſpread abroad falſe doctrine, &amp;c. Ch.</hi> 15.7.</p>
                  <p>The Lord hath made all things for his own ſake, yea euen the wicked for the day of euil. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.4.</p>
                  <p>The Lord hath made euen both theſe, the eare hearing, and the eye ſeeing. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.12. <hi>See in the letter A. A childe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lord is farre from the wicked: but he eareth the praier of the righteous. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.29.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:12612:53"/>
                  <p>The Lorde will deſtroy the houſe of proud men: but he will eſtabliſh the border of the widdow, <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.25.</p>
                  <p>The Lord will not famiſhe the ſoule of the righteous, but he thruſteth away the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the wicked. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10.3.</p>
                  <p>The lot cauſeth contentions to ceaſe, yea it endeth the ſtrife betwixt the mightie. <hi>To wit, in ſuch caſes as can not by ordinarie courſe of triall bee iudged and compounded C.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Whereof reade verſe</hi> 17. <hi>in H. He that is firſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lot is caſt into the lap, but the whole diſpoſition thereof is from the Lord. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.33.</p>
                  <p>The lying lipes are abhomination to the Lord; but they that deale truly are his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The M</head>
                  <p>The memoriall of the iuſt ſhall <hi>(continue)</hi> as ableſſing, <hi>(that is, God ſhalbe praiſed in the honorable and thankefull remembrace of them)</hi> but the name of the wicked ſhal rott) <hi>that is, there ſhall be no gratfull mention made of them in the church of God; nay they ſhall heare their iuſt and deſerued reproch. Chap.</hi> 10.7.</p>
                  <p>The mouth of a righteous man is a well ſpring of life <hi>(that is, he is plentiful in grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12612:53"/>ſpeach to his owne comfort and to the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and refreſhing of other)</hi> but iniquitie couereth the mouth of the wicked. <hi>(that is, his owne hurtfull ſpeaches and actions do as it were choake and ſmother himſelfe. Read in B. bleſſings. &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 10.6.11.</p>
                  <p>The mouth of ſtrange women, is as a deepe pit, he with whome the Lord is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly angry <hi>(or whome he hath in deteſtation)</hi> ſhall fall there. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.14.</p>
                  <p>The mouth of the iuſt man will be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in wiſdome: but it <hi>(that is wiſdome)</hi> is ent off from the tongue <hi>(that ſpeaketh)</hi> fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things. <hi>That is, to ſay, wiſdome can no more fructifie and proſper there then tho bough which is proyned and out off from the bodie of the tree. Ch.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Looke the</hi> 32. <hi>verſe The lippes of the righteousdo knowe, or (ſhall finde) fauour &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The N</head>
                  <p>THE name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower the righteous runneth vnto it, and is exalted. <hi>That is, he is ſet in a high ſafe place. Ch.</hi> 18.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The P</head>
                  <p>THe path (<hi>(or cauſie-way</hi> (of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is to decline from euill: he keepeth oule that keepeth his way. <hi>For on either
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12612:54"/>hand of this cauſie which god hath pitued for the righteous, are nothing but deepe gulfs and quagmires to ſwallow vp thoſe that ſlippe aſide. Ch.</hi> 16.17.</p>
                  <p>The patient abiding of the righteous ſhall be gladnes: but the hope of the wicked ſhall periſh. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.28.</p>
                  <p>The perſon that is full deſpiſeth an hony combe: but vnto the hungry ſoule euerie bitter thing is ſweete. <hi>Ch.</hi> 27.7.</p>
                  <p>The perſon that trauelleth trauelleth for himſelf, <hi>Or rather thus is the latter part of the ſonte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce requireth.</hi> He that is trouble in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth trouble vpon himſelfe: for his mouth, <hi>(that is; the troubleſome ſpeach of his mouth)</hi> reboundeth <hi>(or recoileth)</hi> back vpon him. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.26.</p>
                  <p>The pleaſure <hi>(or fauourable good will)</hi> of the King is toward a wiſe ſeruant, but his wrath ſhall be againſt him that is lewde, <hi>or that cauſeth ſhame. To wit, to himſelfe and others by his fooliſh dealing Chap.</hi> 14.35.</p>
                  <p>The poore man and the craftes man <hi>(in ſuch ſenſe as we vſe to call artificers handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftes men) liueth by his daye laboure, and euerie other that vſeth a more liberall &amp; gainfull ſkill)</hi> they meete together, the Lord lighteneth the eyes of them both, <hi>that is, God maketh this difference and diſt inction of callings &amp; giueth to euery one their knowledge
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12612:54"/>and ſkill and what ſoeuer good ſucceſſe they haue and therefore either ſorte are admoniſhed to vſe their labour and ſkill to the glorie of God and theire owne mutuall comfort in him. Ch.</hi> 29.13. <hi>Reade Exod:</hi> 31.1.2.3.4.5.6. <hi>and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 28.24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The poore man is hated euen of his own neighbour, but the friendes of the rich are many. <hi>That is, both far and neere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that ſinneth <hi>thus, (to wit, hating the poor man)</hi> ſhall be deſpiſed of his neighbour, but he <hi>(or as touching him)</hi> that ſheweth mercie to the poore, bleſſed is he. <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.21.</p>
                  <p>The poore man ſpeaketh with prayers <hi>(or by way of intreatie and ſupplications.)</hi> but the rich man anſwereth roughly, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.23.</p>
                  <p>The preparation of the heart <hi>(or as the word ſignifieth, the muſtering of the thoughtes and deuices thereof)</hi> are in man: but the ſpeach of the tongue is from the Lord. <hi>That is, no thought taketh effect but by his bleſſing. Ch.</hi> 16.1 <hi>We are therefore to commit the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of both thoughts, words &amp; works vnto him. Read in C. Comit &amp;c, And in A. Al the waies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The pride of man doth bring him loue, but honor ſupporteth <hi>(or holdeth vp)</hi> him that is humbled in ſpirit. <hi>That is to ſay, God giueth honour, &amp; honorablie eſteeming them wil vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them. Ch.</hi> 29.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The R</head>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:12612:55"/>
                  <p>The reward of humilitie <hi>(or of mekenes)</hi> &amp; of the feare of the Lord is riches &amp; honour and life. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.4,</p>
                  <p>The rich and the poore meete together, the Lord is the maker of them all, <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.2. <hi>That is, he doth not only giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their being but alſo to be euen ſuch as they are.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The riches of vanitie <hi>(that is, which are gotten by any vniuſt and deceitfull means)</hi> ſhall be diminiſhed: but he that gathereth with the hand <hi>(that is, by honeſt labour)</hi> ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe them, <hi>Ch.</hi> 13.11.</p>
                  <p>The rich man is wiſe in his owne conceit <hi>(that is, be thinketh himſelfe ſo much the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer or better man as he is richer)</hi> but the poore man that hath vnderſtanding can trie him. <hi>or ſearch out what is in him. Chapter.</hi> 28.11.</p>
                  <p>The rich mans riches are his ſtrong city, and as an high wall in his imagination. <hi>Ch.</hi> 18.11.</p>
                  <p>The rich mans riches are his ſtrong citie, &amp; that which feareth <hi>(or daunteth)</hi> the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is their pouertie. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10.15.</p>
                  <p>The rich ruleth ouer the poore, and the borrower is made a ſeruant to the man that lendeth, <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.7.</p>
                  <p>The righteous eateth to the contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his minde: but the belly of the wicked ſhall want. <hi>Ch.</hi> 13.25.</p>
                  <p>The righteous eſcapeth out of trouble and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:12612:55"/>the wicked commeth in his ſteade, <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.8.</p>
                  <p>The righteous is more excellent then his neighboure: but the waye of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deceaueth them. <hi>Ch.</hi> 12.26.</p>
                  <p>The righteous knoweth the cauſe of the poore, <hi>(that is, he mindeth it and ſearcheth it out with a minde to ſuccour them in the way of iuſtice, as Iob.</hi> 29.16) but the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked regardeth not to knowe it. <hi>Chapter.</hi> 29.7. <hi>Read Luk.</hi> 18.4.</p>
                  <p>The righteouſneſſe of the vpright <hi>(or entier and perfect man)</hi> directeth his way: but the wicked falleth in his owne wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.5. <hi>And againe in the next verſe.</hi> The righteouſneſſe of the iuſt ſhall deliuer them: but the wicked ſhall fall in his owne wickedneſſe. <hi>Read alſo Ch.</hi> 26.27. <hi>He that diggeth &amp;c. and Ch.</hi> 11.17.18.19. and <hi>Ch.</hi> 12.20. <hi>and.</hi> 13.6. <hi>and.</hi> 21.7.</p>
                  <p>The righteous ſhal neuer be moued: but the wicked ſhall not dwell in the land. <hi>(To wit, ſo conſtantlie rooted and ſettled as the other, Ch.</hi> 10.30.</p>
                  <p>The righteous teacheth the houſe of the wicked, but <hi>God</hi> ouerthroweth the wicked for their euill. <hi>Or rather thus.</hi> He that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth the wicked for their euill, <hi>(or to their owne hurt, that is to ſay, the iuſt God)</hi> maketh the righteous wiſe by the houſe of the wicked. <hi>That is; by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12612:56"/>of his iudgmentes executed vpon them, be teacheth them to beware. Chapter.</hi> 21.12.</p>
                  <p>The robberie of the wicked ſhall abide with them <hi>(or be as it were at hoſt with him, to wit, as an euill gueſt which oweth him a miſchiefe)</hi> be cauſe they refuſe to execute iudgemente, <hi>Ch.</hi> 21.7. <hi>Reade Iſai:</hi> 33.1. <hi>and Haback:</hi> 2.8.9.10.11.12.</p>
                  <p>The rod and correction giueth wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but a childe ſet at libertie maketh his mother aſhamed. <hi>Ch:</hi> 29.15. <hi>The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof may well be comprehended in the next verſe, in the wordes following.</hi> When the wicked increaſe, <hi>(to wit, as well in age and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as in number)</hi> tranſgreſſion increaſeth: but the righteous ſhall ſee their fall. <hi>And therefore alſo to good purpoſe are Parentes exhorted to vſe correction as it followeth in the 17, verſe. Correct thy ſonne. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The S</head>
                  <p>The Sacrifice of the wicked <hi>(that is, all his religion being outward and without faith and repentance)</hi> is abhomination to the Lord: but the prayer of the righteous <hi>(that is, his ſpirituall worſhippe performed in trueth though not with ſo great oſtentation as the wicked vſe)</hi> is acceptable to him. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.8.</p>
                  <p>The ſacrifice of the wicked is an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:12612:56"/>how much more when he bringeth it with a wicked minde? <hi>Or in a wicked manner, that is, profanely and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſlie, as the people in the time that Malachi propheſied, Ch.</hi> 21.27. <hi>Read Mal: Ch:</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>The ſinner deſpiſeth his neighbour: but he that hath mercie on the poore is bleſſed. 14.21. <hi>Looke before. The poore man is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſlouthfull hideth his hand in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>(or platter)</hi> it grieueth him to put it <hi>(or he is as one tyred with putting it)</hi> to his mouth againe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 26.15. <hi>And again Ch:</hi> 19.24.</p>
                  <p>The ſlouthfull hideth his hand in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>(or platter as before)</hi> and bringeth it not backe to his mouth againe. <hi>That is to ſay, there are a number that doo ſo cocker them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their ſluggiſhneſſe, that minding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to eate and drinke, and to make much of themſelues, can yet hardly finde in their heart to take any paines about that which is for mans neceſſitie: ſuch as are all voluptuous Epicures, carpett knightes &amp;c. It is a liuely and taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting deſcription of ſuch kinde of people: as are alſo the reſt that followe: all tending to prouoke vnto diligence and watchfullneſſe in al good and holy duties to the glorie of God and to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon benefit of others and our ſelues. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſlouthfull man ſayeth, a fierce lion is in the way; a lion is euen is the ſtreetes.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:12612:57"/>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.13.</p>
                  <p>The ſlouthfull man ſayeth, a lion is without, I ſhoulde be ſlaine in the ſtreate. <hi>(That is, he thinketh it would be ſo, if he ſhould but ſet his foote without doores, ſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any good and holy worke. Chapter.</hi> 22.13.</p>
                  <p>The ſlouthfull man turneth himſelfe in his bed, as the doore turneth on the hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>That is, he keepeth his bed as if he were faſtened to it, Ch.</hi> 26.14.</p>
                  <p>The ſlouthfull man which will not plow becauſe of winter, he ſhall begge in ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer becauſe he <hi>(ſhall haue)</hi> nothing, <hi>to witte, to releeue and helpe himſelfe. Ch:</hi> 20.4.</p>
                  <p>The ſluggard <hi>(or ſlouthfull man as before)</hi> is wiſer in his owne conceite then ſeauen men that can render a ſenſible reaſon. <hi>Ch.</hi> 26.16.</p>
                  <p>The ſoule of the ſlouthfull man luſteth, but ſhall haue nothing: but the ſoule of ſuch as be diligent ſhall be made fat. <hi>That it, they ſhall be ſtored with plenty. Chapter.</hi> 13.4.</p>
                  <p>The ſoule of the wicked wiſheth euill <hi>(to wit, through that enuie and malice which reigneth in him,)</hi> his neighboure can not ſeeme worthy to be fauoured in his eies. <hi>Ch.</hi> 21.10.</p>
                  <p>The ſpirite of a man will ſuſtaine his in firmitie <hi>(that is, will yeelde him comforte in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12612:57"/>all his affections)</hi> but awounded ſpirite who can ſuſteine it? Ch. 18.14.</p>
                  <p>The ſteppes of man are from the Lord, <hi>(that is, they are ruled and moderated by him):</hi> but what doth man vnderſtande of his <hi>(that is, the Lordes) way? Ch.</hi> 20.24. <hi>A ſentence of exceeding weight to moue all men to be wiſe vnto ſobrietie and to humble our ſelues vnder the mighty hand of God. Read Ch.</hi> 1.91.2.3.4.9. <hi>and Iere:</hi> 10.23. <hi>and Iob.</hi> 26.14. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The T</head>
                  <p>THe talking <hi>(or wordes)</hi> of the wicked <hi>are</hi> to lie in waite for bloode <hi>(that is, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray innocent bloode)</hi> but the mouth of the righteous will deliuer them. <hi>To wit, them whoſe life the wicked ſeeke howe they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trappe. Ch.</hi> 12.6.</p>
                  <p>The thoughts of the diligent are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether profitable: but all the thoughtes of him that is raſhe <hi>(or headdy) tende</hi> to meere pouertie <hi>Ch.</hi> 21.5.</p>
                  <p>The thoughtes of the iuſt are right; but the councels of the wicked are deceit. <hi>That is verie deceitfull. Ch:</hi> 12.5.</p>
                  <p>The thoughtes of the wicked are abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lorde: but the pure <hi>haue</hi> pleaſaunt wordes. <hi>Ch,</hi> 15.26. <hi>Read. Ch.</hi> 25.11, 12. <hi>A word ſpoken &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:12612:58"/>
                  <p>The congue of the iuſt man is as the moſt choice <hi>(or fined)</hi> ſiluer but the heart of the wicked is verie little worth. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.20.</p>
                  <p>The tongue of the wiſe vſeth knowledge aright: but the mouth of fooles bableth out fooliſhnes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.2.</p>
                  <p>The treaſures of wickedneſſe profitte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: but righteouſneſſe deliuereth from death. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The V</head>
                  <p>THe vnderſtanding of them that haue it is a well ſpringe of life, <hi>(to teach many in the way of life:)</hi> but the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of fooles is <hi>(a well spring)</hi> of follie. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.22.</p>
                  <p>The vnthrifty man <hi>(or ſuch a one as is an inordinat and lawleſſe perſon)</hi> a verie wicked man <hi>(or as we may ſay, one of no reckoning, a man good for nothing, of a reprobate minde)</hi> he walketh with a frowarde mouth.</p>
                  <p>He maketh a ſigne <hi>(or twinkleth)</hi> with his eies; he ſignifieth <hi>(or ſpeaketh after a ſort)</hi> with his feet, he inſtructeth with his fingers: <hi>that is to ſay, he is altogether addicted to that which is naught: which K. S. doth liuely ſet forth by noting the propenſion and bending of all his bodily partes and members that way: Like to the earneſt archer who hauing deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his arrowe out of the bowe, ſheweth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12612:58"/>how faine he would haue his arrowe euen hitte the marke if it might be, by bowing his bodie this way and that way all the vvhile his ſhaft is flying.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Lewde <hi>(or froward)</hi> thinges beeing in his heart, he imagineth <hi>(or practiſeth)</hi> that which is euill at all times; <hi>(that is, ſo often as he can get any opportunity:)</hi> he raiſeth vp <hi>(or ſendeth)</hi> contentions. <hi>That is, matter of contention and ſtrife which is a ſpeciall miſchiefe againſt humaine ſocietie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore ſhal his deſtruction come ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilie; he ſhall be deſtroyed ſodenly <hi>(or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly cruſhed in peeces)</hi> without recouerie. <hi>So that an irrecouerable puniſhment belongeth to the deſperate and graceleſſe ſinner. Chap.</hi> 6.13.14.15.</p>
                  <p>The vprightneſſe <hi>(or integrity)</hi> of the iuſt ſhall guide them <hi>(or lead them foorth, to wit in the way of happineſſe)</hi> but the froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of tranſgreſſours ſhall deſtroy them. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Read verſes</hi> 5.6. <hi>The righteouſnes of the vpright, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The VV</head>
                  <p>THE way of a foole is right in his owne eies: but he that he arkeneth to counſel is wiſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.15.</p>
                  <p>The way of a ſlouthfull man is as a hedge of thornes: but the way of the righteous is
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12612:59"/>plaine, <hi>(or as a cauſied way. Chap.</hi> 15.19.</p>
                  <p>The way of life is on high <hi>(or vpward)</hi> to the prudent, that he may auoyde from hell beneath. <hi>(Or which is downward. Chap.</hi> 15.24.</p>
                  <p>The way of ſome is peruerted &amp; ſtrange, <hi>(Or thus.)</hi> Who ſo is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant <hi>(or mutable)</hi> in his way, he is alſo ſtrange <hi>(to wit, from pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or ſinceritie)</hi> but he is pure whoſe worke is right. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.8.</p>
                  <p>The way of the Lord <hi>(that is, the courſe which the Lord taketh in his adminiſtration and gouernement)</hi> is ſtrength to the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>(or entire man: that is, it is for their ſafety and preſeruation)</hi> but it is deſtruction to the workers of iniquitie. <hi>That is, ſo God vſeth to deale with the vvicked. Chap.</hi> 10.29.</p>
                  <p>The way of the wicked is an abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Lord: but he loueth him that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth righteouſneſſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.9.</p>
                  <p>The waies of man <hi>(that is, of euery man,)</hi> are before the eies of the Lord, and he ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all his pathes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.21.</p>
                  <p>The wicked man deſireth defence <hi>(or ſafegard)</hi> from euill, but the roote of the righteous <hi>(that is, that onely wherein they are rooted and grounded, to witte, the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and prouident care of the Lorde)</hi> giueth it. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.12.</p>
                  <p>The wicked flie when none purſueth: but the righteous are as the yong Lion that is
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:12612:59"/>bould. <hi>Chap.</hi> 28.1.</p>
                  <p>The wicked <hi>(or harmefull man)</hi> giueth heede to the troubleſome lippe, <hi>(that is, to him whoſe talke tendeth to the troubling and moleſting of men,)</hi> and a man of falſhood <hi>(i. a liar)</hi> hearkeneth to the tongue of miſerie. <hi>That is, to the miſerable or wretched tongue, which cauſeth miſerie, &amp;c. Chap.</hi> 17.4.</p>
                  <p>The wicked ouerthrow themſelues ſo that they be not: but the houſe of the righteous ſhall ſtand. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Reade in G. God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthroweth &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The wicked ſhal be a ranſome for the iuſt, and the tranſgreſſor in ſtead of the righteous. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.18.</p>
                  <p>The wicked ſhalbe caſt away for his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: <hi>Or rather thus.</hi> The wicked thruſteth forth himſelfe <hi>(or inforceth himſelfe)</hi> to his own hurt: but the righteous hath hope, <hi>(or as the word ſignifieth, findeth a refuge or reskue)</hi> in his death. <hi>that is, in his greateſt perill. Chap.</hi> 14.32.</p>
                  <p>The wicked thought <hi>(or deede)</hi> of a foole is ſinne; <hi>(that is, a ſinne worthy to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:)</hi> but the wickedneſſe of a ſcornefull man is abhomination, <hi>That is to ſay, it is greatly to be abhorred aboue the ſinne of the fooliſh and ignorant man. Chap.</hi> 24.9.</p>
                  <p>The wicked worketh a deceitfull worke, <hi>(that is, the fruit and reward thereof ſhall be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12612:60"/>farre other then he looketh for)</hi> but the reward of him that ſoweth righteouſneſſe is ſure. <hi>Or true and faithfull. That is, it ſhall be the ſame vvhich according to Gods mercifull and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous promiſe they looke and waite for: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which followeth in the next verſe.</hi> He that is firme <hi>(or conſtant)</hi> in the worke of righteouſneſſe <hi>(that is, in giuing to euery one their due, yea in ſhewing mercy and liberalitie to the poore and oppreſſed) (ſoweth)</hi> to life: but he that followeth euill, doth it to his owne death. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.18.19.</p>
                  <p>The wiſedome of the prudent is to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, <hi>(or wiſely to take heede to)</hi> his way: but the fooliſhneſſe of fooles <hi>(tendeth)</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.8.</p>
                  <p>The wiſe in heart ſhalbe called prudent, &amp; the ſweetnes of the lips <hi>(that is, gratious vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſpeech, or holy eloquence)</hi> increaſeth, <hi>(or furthereth)</hi> doctrine. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.21.</p>
                  <p>The wiſe in heart will receiue commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: but the fooliſh in talke, <hi>(that is, he which from the ſtubbornneſſe of his heart mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mureth againſt good precepts and inſtructions)</hi> ſhall be beaten. <hi>(or procureth his owne trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) Chap.</hi> 10.8.</p>
                  <p>The wordes of a talebearer are as flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, <hi>(or like to the wordes of ſuch as are much broken vvith afflictions, that is to ſay, he play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the counterfette notablie, creeping as it were
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12612:60"/>into the mouth of men to get ſomething; and therefore vvhiſpereth here and there preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding much good ſooth, &amp;c.)</hi> but they goe downe into the bowels of the belly. <hi>That is, the vvordes of ſuch are as poyſon to hurte very deadlie. Chap.</hi> 18.8. <hi>And Chap.</hi> 26.22.</p>
                  <p>The wordes which the mouth of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent man <hi>(ſpeaketh)</hi> are like deepe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; the welſpring of wiſedome is as a flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing floode. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.4.</p>
                  <p>The wrath of a king is as meſſengers of death, but a wiſe man will pacifie it. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.14. <hi>But on the contrarie: verſe</hi> 15. <hi>Reade in the letter I. In the light of the kinges countenance is life, &amp;c. Read alſo Chap.</hi> 19.12. <hi>The Kinges vvrath, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a way which <hi>(ſeemeth)</hi> right before man, but the iſſue <hi>(or ende)</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>(is the iſſue)</hi> of the waies of death. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.12. <hi>The vvhich ſentence is further declared in the</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 14. <hi>verſes next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Reade in E. Euen in laughing, &amp;c. And, The heart that declineth, &amp;c. Reade alſo the ſame repeated againe. Chap.</hi> 16.25.</p>
                  <p>There is no wiſedome, neyther vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding nor counſell againſt the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>The horſe is prepared <hi>(or made fit)</hi> for the day of battell but ſaluation is from the Lord. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.30.31.</p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:12612:61"/>
                  <p>There is that boaſteth himſelfe to be rich and hath nothing, and that feineth himſelfe poore hauing greate riches. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.7.</p>
                  <p>There is that ſcattereth and yet is more increaſed. and <hi>(there is)</hi> that ſpareth more then is right <hi>(or that withouldeth himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is right)</hi> only to pouertie. <hi>that is, &amp; yet he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to meere pouertie. C.</hi> 11.24.</p>
                  <p>There is that ſpeaketh wordes like the prickings <hi>(or ſtabbings)</hi> of the ſworde; but the tongue of wiſe men is health. <hi>That is, it ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thoſe thinges which may be compared to a healthful medicine Ch.</hi> 12.18.</p>
                  <p>There ſhall no trouble be caſt vpon the iuſt <hi>(to wit, by hap hazard or chaunce medley as we ſay,)</hi> but the wicked ſhall be full of euill. <hi>That is, God will many wayes aboue that they looke for, plague &amp; puniſhe them C.</hi> 12.21.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſixe thinges doth the Lord hate, yea ſeauen are abhomination to his ſoule,</p>
                  <p>The hautie eyes, a lying tongue; and hands that ſhed innocent bloud:</p>
                  <p>An heart that imagineth <hi>(or contrineth)</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deuiſes; feete that be ſwift in running to miſchiefe:</p>
                  <p>A falſe witnes that breatheth forth <hi>(or craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily forgeth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pacteth lies</hi> &amp; he that raiſeth vp (<hi>or cauſeth</hi> (coutentions <hi>(to come)</hi> betwixt bretheren. <hi>Ch.</hi> 6.16.17.18.19.</p>
                  <p>They that are froward in heart are abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:12612:61"/>to the Lord: but they that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>(or enter)</hi> in the way, are his delight. <hi>or ſuch as he fauourably accepteth. Chapter,</hi> 11.20.</p>
                  <p>They that forſake the law praiſe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: but they that keepe the lawe ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <hi>(or, are as it were in conflict)</hi> againſt them. <hi>Chapt.</hi> 28.4.</p>
                  <p>Thine owne friende and thy fathers friend, <hi>(to wit, whoſe friendſhip deſcendeth as it were hereditarily to the)</hi> forſake thou not, neither go to thy brothers houſe in the day of thy calami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie: better is a neighbour that is neare, then a brother farre off <hi>Ch.</hi> 27.10.</p>
                  <p>Thornes and ſnares <hi>(or thornie ſnares)</hi> are in the way of the froward; <hi>(to wit, to pricke &amp; ſnare themſelues withal as a fruite of their pride &amp;c.</hi> but he that keepeth his ſoule <hi>(that is to ſay, from ſin)</hi> ſhal be far from them. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.5.</p>
                  <p>Through wiſdome the houſe is builded, &amp; by vnderſtanding it is eſtabliſhed.</p>
                  <p>By knowledge alſo thy chambers ſhal be filled with all pretious and pleaſant riches. <hi>Ch.</hi> 24.3.4.</p>
                  <p>Tough hand be to hand <hi>(that is, though they ioyne in mutuall helpe and aſſiſtance)</hi> the wicked ſhall not be vnpuniſhed, but the ſeed of the righteous eſcapeth. <hi>Or is deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. To wit, though one cannot helpe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour an other they being oftentimes ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> &amp;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:12612:62"/>diſperſed: For God is their deliuerer &amp; auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Ch.</hi> 11.21.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not remoue the ancient bounds which thy fathers haue made. <hi>Or ſet and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</hi> 22.28.</p>
                  <p>To do iuſtice and iudgment is more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Lord then ſacrifice. <hi>Chapter,</hi> 21.3.</p>
                  <p>To haue reſpect of perſon is not good, a man ſhould <hi>(then)</hi> tranſgreſſe for a morſell of breade. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28.21. <hi>And Chap.</hi> 24.23. <hi>it is one of thoſe thinges which are ſaide to belong to the wiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Trauell not too much to be rich; <hi>(or toile not thy ſelfe that thou mighteſt grow rich)</hi> ceaſe from thy wiſdome, <hi>to wit, from thy naturall wiſdome in compaſſing ſea and land (as it were) to get riches.</hi> Wilt thou cauſe thine eyes to fly toward them? <hi>to wit, as the greedie foule haſteth hir flight to the pray;</hi> they are not <hi>(that is, by and by they are gon; to wit, as birdes ſkar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before they canbe ſeazed on)</hi> for they doe ſpeedely betake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to their wings &amp; as an eagle they flye into the ayer, <hi>C.</hi> 23.4.5</p>
                  <p>Truſt in the Lord with all thy hearte, and leane not to thy owne wiſdome. In all thy wayes acknowledge him and he will direct thy goings. <hi>Ch.</hi> 3.5.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:12612:62"/>
                  <head>Here followeth the whole <hi>thirtie Chapter as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing</hi> wholly to <hi>this letter.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wordes of <hi>Agur</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iakeh,</hi> a collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>or Propheſi:</hi> the ſpech <hi>(or ſaying)</hi> of man <hi>(that is, al ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſpeach or holy doctrin and propheſie which any man vttereth)</hi> is of Ithiel, of Ithiell <hi>(I ſay)</hi> and of vcal. <hi>That is, of him to whome theſe names doe moſt properly agree; euen of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie GOD by the gratious preſence and power of his grace; that is, to ſay in plaine words, GOD is the author of all propheſie. Which propoſition he confirmeth firſt from his owne example as followeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Surely <hi>(ſaith Agur)</hi> I am a beaſt rather then a man; neither haue I the vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of man. <hi>That is, which is worthie and beſeeming a man according to that excellency wherein God firſt created Adam. Agur ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12612:63"/>in theſe words acknowledgeth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waileth his natural corruption and deprauati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo teacheth all men by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple what we are to doe, both in theſe words and further as it followeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> haue I learned wiſdom, or attayned to the knowledge of holy things. <hi>That is, either of God or of his will or of any thing belonging to his heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: he meaneth that he hath no true and perfect knowledg nor any pure deſire to know a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe things by natural iuſtinct, or mother wit as we ſay: to the further diſabling whereof it followeth in the next wordes as it were in a generall challenge againſt all men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who (to wit, of al the ſons &amp; poſterity of Adam)</hi> hath aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded? who hath gathered the wind in his fiſts? who hath bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the waters in his garment? Who hath eſtabliſhed any of the ends <hi>(or bounds)</hi> of the earth? what is his name? and what is his ſonnes name? if thou canſt tell? <hi>As though he ſhould ſay none cant each man knowledge nor renew his heart vnto God but he that hath doone and can doe all theſe things: that is, none but God himſelfe, and he whome God hath ſent his only ſon Ieſus Chriſt through the moſt powerfull grace of his holie ſpirit by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of his bleſſed word: the commendation &amp; vſe whereof followeth in the next verſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:12612:63"/>
                  <p>Euery worde of God <hi>(or the whole worde of God)</hi> is verie pure, he is a ſhielde to thoſe that truſt in him. <hi>Or that make him their refuge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Put thou nothing to his wordes, leaſt he reproue thee, neither be thou found a liar.</p>
                  <p>Two thinges doo I deſier of thee; withholde them not from me vntill I die. <hi>That is ſo longe as I liue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Remoue farre from me vanitie, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie lying matter: giue me not pouertie nor riches; feede me with foode conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for me: <hi>(or with food meaſured out and appointed for me:)</hi> Leaſt I be full, and make a lie and ſay, who is the Lorde? or leaſt I be poore and ſteale, and lay holde of the name of my God. <hi>To wit, as one that abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it to ſerue his owne turne by forſwearing and curſing himſelfe that he may ſeeme guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and go ſtill in the name and account of an honeſt man &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Accuſe thou not a ſeruant to his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>(or as the worde is more generall, hurt him not with the tongue;)</hi> leaſt he curſe thee, and thou be founde to haue offended. <hi>To wit, by thy falſe or vncharitable accuſation, whereby the poore ſeruant is wronged and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to wiſh euill againſt thee: the which thinge as Agur giueth to vnderſtand doth
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12612:64"/>both prouoke the lorde to diſpleaſure and alſo is iuſtly reprochfull amonge men. And note her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, how great care the Lorde hath of cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſocietie, when as he can not beare that he which is in the loweſt ſtate and condition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt ſhoulde be vncurteouſely dealt withall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a generation which curſeth their father, and doth not bleſſe their mother:</p>
                  <p>There is a generation which is pure in the owne eies <hi>(or conceite)</hi> though it be not waſhed from the filthineſſe of it.</p>
                  <p>There is a generation whoſe eyes are verie hautie, and whoſe eyelides doo lifte vp themſelues alofte:</p>
                  <p>There is a generation whoſe teeth are as ſwordes, and their chawes as kniues to eate vp the poore from the earth and the needie from among men.</p>
                  <p>The horſe-leach hath two daughters <hi>(that is, a two forked tongue)</hi> Giue, Giue, <hi>(that is, it is vnſatiable in ſucking of bloode, And beſide this)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are three thinges that will not be ſatiſfied, yea foure which ſay not hoe, <hi>(or it is enoughe)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The graue, and the barren wombe; the earth alſo is not ſatiſfied with water, and the fire ſaieth not hoe, <hi>or enoughe</hi>)</p>
                  <p>The eye which mocketh his father or
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:12612:64"/>deſpiſeth the obedience of his mother <hi>(that is to obey his mother)</hi> the rauens of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhall picke it out, and the yonge eagles ſhall eate it. <hi>It ſeemeth that Agur meaneth that theſe rauening fowles ſhall ſtriue for it, and the one take it from the other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There be three thinges hid from me, yea foure which I knowe not:</p>
                  <p>The way of an eagle in the ayer, the way of a ſerpent vpon a rocke, the way of a ſhippe in the hearte of the ſea <hi>(that is, in the deepe ſea)</hi> and the way of a man with a maide.</p>
                  <p>The way of an adulterous woman is on this wiſe <hi>(to wit, as followeth):</hi> ſhe eateth, and wipeth her mouth; and ſayeth, I haue not committed iniquitie. <hi>That is, ſhe ſinneth warily and pretendeth great innocencie if ſhe be charged with her ſinne, and therefore it is hard to finde it out. But God ſeeth it and will bring both the adultereſſe and the adulterer to iudgement, commit they their ſinne in neuer ſo great ſecrete, and how impudently ſo euer they face it out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The earth is moued <hi>(or trembleth and ſhaketh)</hi> vnder three thinges, yea vnder foure, which it is not able to beare: Vnder a ſeruant when he reigneth and a foole when he is filled with meate: Vnder the hatefull woman when ſhe is maried, and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12612:65"/>vnder a handmaide when ſhe is made heier to her miſtreſſe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe foure be ſmall thinges of the earth; yet they are wiſe, yea verie-wiſe <hi>(or full of wiſdome: to wit, as hauing beene taught to be wiſe):</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The piſmiers a people not ſtronge, yet prepare they their meate in ſommer:</p>
                  <p>The conies <hi>(or rather the mice of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teines)</hi> a people not mightie, yet make they their houſes in the rocke:</p>
                  <p>The graſhopper hath no king, yet all his companie goeth forth by bandes:</p>
                  <p>The ſpider taketh holde with her handes, and ſhe is in Kinges palaces. <hi>How much more then doth it beſeeme man, who glorieth in his wiſe dome as the moſt noble creature, to ſhewe forth his wiſdome by a ſingular prouidence and warie circumspection ioyned with a concorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſent and expert diligence in all good of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and duety, both for comfort in peace, and for defence againſt that which woulde annoie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe three thinges order well their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yea foure are comlie in going.</p>
                  <p>An olde lion the ſtrongeſt amonge beaſts, which turneth not backe at the ſight of any.</p>
                  <p>He that is well truſſed in the loynes, <hi>(to wit, the luſtie grayehounde or horſe, it is the periphraſis of ſome ſtronge and ſtately beaſt)</hi> or a goate; and a Kinge againſt whom there
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12612:65"/>is no riſing vp. <hi>That is to ſay, godly forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and courage beſeemeth well the Prince, and holy obedience and ſubmiſion is the ſafetie of the ſubiect: to the which purpoſe is that which followeth in the next twoo verſes which be the laſt of this chapter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If thou haſt bene fooliſh in lifting vp thy ſelfe <hi>(to wit, againſt the King or any in high place aboue thee)</hi> yea if thou haſt <hi>but</hi> thought it; lay thy hande vpon thy mouth. For as when one churneth milke he bringeth forth butter, and as the cruſhing of the noſe cauſeth blood to come forth, ſo the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>(or inforcing of wrath)</hi> bringeth forth ſtrife. <hi>Ch.</hi> 30.32.33. <hi>Read Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>V</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nderſtanding is a well ſpringe of life <hi>&amp;c. Reade in. T. The vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto the horſe belongeth a whippe, to the Aſſe a bridle, and a rodd to the backe of fooles. Ch. 26.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VV</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen a wicked man dieth his hope periſheth; yea his hope of chiefe ſtrength <hi>(that is, his ſtrongeſt or ſtouteſt hope, his hope of greateſt confidence)</hi> periſheth. <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.7.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:12612:66"/>
               <p>When pride commeth then commeth ſhame, <hi>(to wit, to the proud man)</hi> but with the lowly is wiſedome. <hi>(That is, ſuch wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vvhereby he auoideth ſhame, yea for the vvhich he is honoured.) Ch:</hi> 11.2.</p>
               <p>When righteous men reioyce <hi>(to vvit, as beeing ſet vp and aduanced by God to beare rule ouer the reſt)</hi> there is great glory <hi>(or much ſtore of thinges for ornament, namely to good men):</hi> but when the wicked riſe vp <hi>(that is, vvhen they are aduanced)</hi> euerie man is priede into. <hi>The meaning is, no man almoſt can holde his owne with quiete becauſe of their couetous oppreſſion and tyrannie. Cha.</hi> 28.12.</p>
               <p>VVhen the righteous are increaſed <hi>(or made great, to wit, in authoritie and honour)</hi> the people reioyce: but when a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man beareth rule, the people ſighe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 29.2.</p>
               <p>VVhen the ſcorner is puniſhed the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh becommeth wiſe; alſo when the wiſe is inſtructed that he may vnderſtand, he <hi>(that is, the fooliſh and ſillie man, or one of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker capacitie and net hardened in wickedneſſe)</hi> will receiue knowledge. <hi>The meaning is, that a more ſimple witted man vvill rather learne by the example and inſtruction that is giuen to another then if he ſhould himſelfe be ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vvith the multitude of vvordes or ouer
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:12612:66"/>ſharply dealte withall. Ch:</hi> 21.11. <hi>Reade al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Ch.</hi> 19.25. <hi>in S. Smite a ſcorner &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the waies of a man pleaſe the Lorde, he will make euen his enemies to be at peace with him. <hi>Ch:</hi> 16.7.</p>
               <p>When the wicked doo increaſe <hi>(to wit, either in continuance of yeares or in greatneſſe of place and honour)</hi> tranſgreſſion increaſeth: <hi>that is, they growe in ſinne and proceed to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter impieties and to more groſſe inhumanities and iniuſtice)</hi> but righteous men ſhall ſee their fall. <hi>Ch:</hi> 29.16.</p>
               <p>When the wicked man commeth then alſo commeth contempt: <hi>That is ſo ſoone as a man ſheweth himſelfe to be a wicked man he maketh himſelfe deſpiſed):</hi> and with the vile man reproch. <hi>That is, ſhame doth accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the man that dealeth vilie or ignominiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Ch:</hi> 18.3.</p>
               <p>When the wicked riſe vp, a man hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe: but when they periſh, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men are increaſed. <hi>That is, they flouriſh and proſper. Ch.</hi> 28.28.</p>
               <p>When thou ſitteſt to eate with a ruler, conſider diligently that which is before thee <hi>(that is feed not gredily or vnaduiſedly:)</hi> Otherwiſe thou <hi>ſhould</hi> deſt <hi>(as it were)</hi> putt a knife to thy throte <hi>(that is, thou ſhouldeſt doe thy ſelfe a miſchiefe)</hi> if thou wouldeſt giue ouer thy ſelfe <hi>(or yeelde)</hi> to thy appetite.</p>
               <p>Be not deſirous of his deintie meates, for
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12612:67"/>it is deceiuable meate. <hi>(That is, it will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make a man forget himſelfe and all good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. &amp;c:</hi> 23.1.2.3.</p>
               <p>Wherefore is there a price in the hand of a foole, ſeeing he hath no heart to get wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? <hi>as though he ſhoulde ſay, it is to no purpoſe in all the worlde; no abundaunce will doo a man good if his minde ſtande not to ſeeke after true wiſdome: and againe, he is vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of any outwarde bleſſing that eſteemeth wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of no worth. Ch.</hi> 17.16.</p>
               <p>Where no wiſe councellers are the people fall: but where there is an excellent coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler <hi>(that is, one of great wiſdome and much experience)</hi> there is health. <hi>Ch:</hi> 11.14.</p>
               <p>Where there be no oxen the cribbe is cleane, <hi>(that is, emptie, he meaneth, there is want of all thinges when huſbandrie is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected)</hi> but much increaſe commeth by the ſtrength of the oxe. <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.4.</p>
               <p>Where there is no viſion <hi>(that is, no true and faithfull preaching of the worde of God)</hi> the people are ſpoiled <hi>(or rifled and left naked)</hi> but he that keepeth the lawe, bleſſed is he. <hi>That is, whoſoeuer he be that heareth and obeyeth the doctrin of the worde of God which is preached and interpreted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Ch.</hi> 29.18.</p>
               <p>Who can ſay, I haue made my hearte cleane; I am cleane from my ſinne? <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:12612:67"/>20.9.</p>
               <p>Wicked men will not vnderſtande <hi>(or regarde)</hi> iudgment <hi>(that is, vvhat is equall and right)</hi> but they that ſeeke the Lord will vnderſtand <hi>(or conſider)</hi> all thinges <hi>(to vvit, leaſt for vvant of aduiſement they ſhoulde doo that vvhich is vnequall or vnmeete, Chap.</hi> 28.5.</p>
               <p>Wine is a mocker, and ſtronge drinke is raging; <hi>(that is, it maketh them that giue themſelues to the immoderat drinking of it ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous and vnrulie)</hi> wherefore he that is deceiued thereby <hi>(or maketh his vagary in it, that is, in bibbing of it)</hi> is not wiſe. <hi>Ch:</hi> 20.1.</p>
               <p>Wiſedome is high to a foole <hi>(that is, it is aboue his reach to conceiue rightly of matters of wiſdome)</hi> he can not open his mouth in the gate. <hi>That is, in the place of iudgment. Ch.</hi> 24.7.</p>
               <p>Wiſedome is in the face of him that hath vnderſtanding <hi>(that is, his ſober and vvel ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed countenaunce is a ſigne that he hath a wiſe heart)</hi> but the eyes of a foole <hi>(are vvandering)</hi> towarde the corners of the worlde. <hi>And this declareth the inconſtancie and lightneſſe of his minde. Ch.</hi> 17.24.</p>
               <p>Wiſedome reſteth in the heart of him that hath vnderſtanding; and that which is within fooles, <hi>(to vvit, their fooliſhneſſe)</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:12612:68"/>will make it ſelfe knowen <hi>(it cannot longe be hidden.) Ch:</hi> 14.33.</p>
               <p>Wiſe men lay vp knowledge <hi>(that is, they doo carefully treaſure or hourd it vp in their heartes for good and profitable vſes as neede ſhall require both for themſelues and others)</hi> but deſtruction is neare to the mouth of a foole. <hi>That is, he is readie to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that which may eaſily hurt himſelfe and others too. Ch:</hi> 10.14.</p>
               <p>Withdrawe thy foote from thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures houſe, leſt he be wearie of thee and hate thee. <hi>Ch.</hi> 25.17. <hi>Read in I. If thou haue founde honie. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Withholde not correction from the childe; if thou ſmite him with the rod he ſhall not dy: <hi>(to vvit, as a malefactour for his vvicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which otherwiſe woulde by all likelihoode increaſe to his deſtruction: yea which is more)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt ſmite him with the rodd, and deliuer his ſoule from hell.</p>
               <p>Withholde not goodneſſe <hi>(that is, bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence)</hi> from the owners thereof <hi>(to wit, from ſuch as ſtand in neede of it; in regarde of which their neceſſitie and by reaſon of thy ſteward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God hath intitled them as the iuſt obiect of thy mercifull liberalitie)</hi> when there is power in thy hand to doo it: <hi>(that is, when thou art able to be beneficiall and helpfull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Say not vnto thy neighbour, goe and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:12612:68"/>come againe, and to morowe I will giue thee; if thou nowe haue it. <hi>Ch:</hi> 3.27.28.</p>
               <p>Without councell thoughtes come to naught: but by the excellencie of councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers <hi>(to wit, when from great wiſdome and experience they giue councell)</hi> a thought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth <hi>(that is, it prospereth or is eſtabliſhed. And then it follovveth:</hi> Ioy commeth to a man by the anſwere of his mouth <hi>(to witt, of a wiſe counceller)</hi> and o howe good <hi>(that is, o howe commodious)</hi> is a worde <hi>(or a thing)</hi> in his due ſeaſon! <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.22.23.</p>
               <p>Without woode <hi>(or when wood faileth)</hi> the fire is quenched, and without a tale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer ſtrife ceaſeth: <hi>(or is whiſt).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As is the deade coale to burning coales, and ſtickes to the fire, ſo is a contentious man for the kindlinge of ſtrife. <hi>Chapter.</hi> 26.20.21.</p>
               <p>With the fruit of his mouth ſhall eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie mans belly be ſatiſfied, and by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe <hi>(or that which commeth)</hi> of his lippes, he ſhall be filled <hi>Ch.</hi> 18.20. <hi>And verſe.</hi> 21. Death and life are in the power of the tongue. <hi>Read in D. Read alſo in A. Aman ſhall be ſatiatie. &amp;c. And againe. A man ſhall eate good thinges, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:12612:69"/>
                  <head>Here followeth the whole laſt <hi>Chapter as principally belonging to this letter: or rather in the greateſt part of it being ſette downe in the order of the whole alphabet from the</hi> 10. <hi>verſe to the end of the chapter as vve reade it in the hebrewe texte.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wordes of Lemuel the Kinge; a propheſie <hi>(or collection and gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together of holy doctrine)</hi> where with his mother taught him.</p>
                  <p>What <hi>(ſhall I ſay)</hi> my ſonne? and what ô ſonne of my wombe? yea what <hi>(ſhall I ſay)</hi> ô ſonne of my vowes? <hi>that is, for whom I doo specially pray and vovve thankes vnto God as hauing thee moſt deare in my deſiers. Here therefore is moſt liuely conteined a moſt godly and tender affectioned care of a mother to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarde her beſt beloued ſonne as one deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous euen by the ſpirit of God to giue him the beſt inſtruction: lett vs therefore verie dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlie hearken to her moſt holy doctrine: firſt, touching publique gonernment to the</hi> 10. <hi>verſe; and then vvhat manner of vvife ſhe woulde haue her ſonne to make his more priuate and particulare choyce of, and hovve they ſhoulde
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:12612:69"/>mutually behaue themſelues the one to the other and towarde their children and whole familie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Giue not thy ſtrength vnto women, nor thy wayes to thoſe which bring Kinges to deſtruction. <hi>That is, to harlottes or any woman that is not thy lawfull wife.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Farre be it from Kinges <hi>ô Lemuel,</hi> farre be it from Kinges to drinke wine; <hi>(to wit, inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately)</hi> and from princes <hi>(farre be)</hi> the deſire of ſtrong drink; <hi>that is, all intemperate deſier which would cauſe the euill effectes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Leaſt he drinke and forget the decree and change <hi>(that is, peruert)</hi> the iudgment of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the children of affliction. <hi>That is, of any that are afflicted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Giue ye ſtrong drink to him that is ready to periſh, and wine to them that haue griefe of minde.</p>
                  <p>Let him drinke that he may forget his po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertie and remember his miſerie no more.</p>
                  <p>Open thy mouth for the dumbe in the cauſe of all the children of deſtruction. <hi>That is, of thoſe that are euen now appoynted or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ouer to be cut off by death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Open thy mouth, iudge righteouſly; and pleade the cauſe of all the poore and needie. <hi>And henceforth followeth the praiſe and deſcription of a gratious woman meete to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:12612:70"/>be the wife of a prince or noble ruler in the land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who ſhall find a vertuous woman ſeeing her price doth farre exceede the pearles? <hi>(or carbuncles) That is all otherpretious things of this world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The heart of her huſband truſteth in her, neither ſhall the ſpoyle be wanting. <hi>that is, through her good huſwiferie he ſhall haue ſo greate abundance as if he had beene ſodenlie inriched by the ſpoyles of ſome enimte ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She wil doe him good, and not euill; all the daies of her life.</p>
                  <p>She ſeeketh wool and flaxe, and worketh it out to the liking of their owne hands.</p>
                  <p>Shee is like the ſhippes of the marchante, She bringeth her foode from a farre.</p>
                  <p>And riſing while it is yet night <hi>(that is, verie earely in the morning)</hi> ſhe giueth her houſhould victual, and taſke to her maides. <hi>That is, ſhe alloweth them meate and vvorke enough.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She conſidereth a fielde <hi>(that is, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie vvhich commeth by the field)</hi> and getteth it <hi>(to vvit, by lavvfull hire or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe)</hi> and with the fruite of her hands <hi>(that is, by the induſtrious labour of her handes)</hi> ſhe plainteth a vineyard.</p>
                  <p>She girdeth her lyons with ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, &amp; ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:12612:70"/>her armes:</p>
                  <p>She taſteth that her marchandiſe is good, her candle therefore is not put out by night. <hi>That is, till the euening be well ſpent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sheputteh her hands to the wherle, and her handes take hould of the ſpindle.</p>
                  <p>She openeth her handes wide to the poore yea ſhe putteth forth both her handes to the needie. <hi>That is, ſhe is verie liberall both in giuing and ſending to them according as ſhe either ſeeth or vnderſtandeth vvhat their need is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She feareth not for her familie becauſe of the ſnow <hi>(that is, leſt any of her houſe ſhould take could and ſo fall into agues or ſicknes for want of meete clothing to keepe them warme againſt the extremitie of winter)</hi> for her whole houſehould is clothed with double apparell. <hi>that is, with garments vvell lined.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She prepareth her ſelfe carpetting ſtuffe, <hi>(or ſtuffe for fine hangings or couerings of beds &amp;c.)</hi> fine ſilke <hi>(or lineſi-cloth ſuch as is fine fuſtion &amp;c.)</hi> and purple coloured is her ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</p>
                  <p>Her huſband is knowne in the gates, when he ſitteth with the Elders of the land.</p>
                  <p>She maketh fine linen cloth and ſelleth it, and girdling, which ſhe deliuereth to the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chant man.</p>
                  <p>Strength &amp; honour <hi>(or gratious and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12612:71"/>behauiour voide of delicate ſoftnes &amp; nicenes)</hi> is her clothing, and ſhe laugheth touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day following. <hi>That is, ſhe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not for the morrowe, but therefully dependeth vpon the prouident care of the Lord, in hope of bleſſing and proſperous ſucceſſe from him, walking in his holy wayes: yea beeing content to leaue all by death or ani other way if need ſo require.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She openeth her mouth with wiſdome, <hi>(that is, verie wiſely)</hi> and the law of grace <hi>(or the doctrine of clemencie or benignitie and gentlenes)</hi> is vpon her tongue. <hi>That is, it ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and guideth her tongue ſo as ſhe doth not vſe any ſhreude or bitter ſpeach, neither dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſhe tumuliuouſly, but is both in worde and deed a teacher and example of holy ſobrietie &amp; modeſtie: a grave worthie to be diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued of women; who are wont verie eaſily &amp; commonly to fault in the looſenes and licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of the tongue. But let vs heare further.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She ouerſeeth the wayes of her houſhold, and eateth not the breade of idleneſſe. <hi>That is, ſhe will not liue idlely and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitably.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Her children riſe vp and call her bleſſed, <hi>(that is, they ſpoake honor ably of her; giving wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe to her greate grace and vertue)</hi> her huſband alſo praiſeth her, ſaying.</p>
                  <p>Many daughters haue done vertuouſly but
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12612:71"/>thou ſurmounteſt them all.</p>
                  <p>Fauour <hi>(that is the vaine and doting liking of men)</hi> is deceitful, and beutie, <hi>(that is, the external cauſe of ſuch doting fauour,)</hi> is vanity <hi>(that is, it is a very vaine thing)</hi> but the woman that feareth the Lord ſhe getteth her ſelfe praiſe.</p>
                  <p>Giue her of the fiuite of her hands, and lether owne workes praiſe her in the gates. <hi>That is, openly, and with the generall conſent of all men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>X</head>
               <head>Y</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg> Ronſharpeneth yron, ſo doth a man ſharpen the face of his friende. <hi>Or rather thus. As</hi> a man ſharpeneth yron with yron, ſo doth the face of his friend <hi>(that is, his preſence and familiaritie)</hi> ſharpen a man. <hi>To wit, both to the more cleare vnderſtanding of matters vvhich by himſelfe alone he could not ſo vvell ſee into, and alſo to the increaſe of comfort &amp; incouragement to the enterpriſing &amp; following of ſuch good actions as are to be performed by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To God only wiſe be all glorie and praiſe both nowe and for euer. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:72"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 127.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>A ſong of degrees: that is, <hi>A verie excellent ſong for</hi> Salomon.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onteining in it this moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrine to teach King <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in his time and thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth both high and lowe in all times that the whole proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, increaſe, and wellfare, both of priuate families and alſo of the Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, as well in peace as in warre, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth altogether vpon the gratious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and bleſſing of God: without the which al meanes whatſoeuer, are vaine and voide of all good and comfortable effect. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that in all thinges, both with means, and aboue all meanes, God is humbly to be ſought of his people, by faithfull zealous and conſtant prayer; walking dutifully before him in thoſe holy wayes which he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs to walke in, and to the which he hath promiſed his bleſſing.</p>
            <div type="hymn">
               <pb facs="tcp:12612:72"/>
               <opener>
                  <hi>It may beſonge to the tune of</hi> the tenne commandements.</opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>1</label> 
                     <hi>EXcept the Lorde the houſe doo builde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The builders doo but build in vaine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Like vaine it is to watch citties,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If God doo not the ſame maintaine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>2</label> 
                     <hi>Thinke it but vaine to riſe betimes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eke thinke it vaine to ly downe late:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Though men doo eat their breade with care,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their care can not vpholde their ſtate.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gods fauour is the onlie spring,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From whence all bliſſe to vs doth flowe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Seeke to him then; on him depende,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such ſhall haue reſt both high and lowe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>3</label> 
                     <hi>Marke alſo what I ſhall you tell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A thing right worthy great regard:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>None can giue children but the Lorde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The fruite of wombe is his revvarde.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>4</label> 
                     <hi>As heritage God doth them giue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Indovving parentes vvith their aide;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To be as ſhaftes in ſtrong mans hand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To th'end they ſhould not be diſmaide.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>5</label> 
                     <hi>O bleſſed they vvhoſe quiuers haue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such vvarlike arrovves in good ſtore:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They ſhall preuaile againſt their foes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And vanquiſh them at their ovvne dore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:73"/>
            <head>Faultes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Pag. 26. lin. 25. for they, Read thy. Pag. 65. lin. 27. for, that is actions. Read that is the actions. Pag. 73 lin. 15. for vſualle, Read vſually. &amp; lin. 22. for meate, read meane. Pag. 74. lin. 8. for ſtrange woman, read a ſtrang woman. Pag. 80. lin. 7, put out and. And in the ſame pag, lin 11. put out (<hi>or.</hi> Pag. 83. lin. 26. for were a, read were in a. Pag. 84. lin. 26. put out the, Pag. 87, lin. 30. for oule, read his ſoule. Pag, 88, lin, 11, for, The perſon that trauelleth for himſelfe, read The perſon that trauelleth, trauelleth for himſelfe. pag, 89, lin, 26, for prird, read pride. pag, 93, lin, 30, for, euen is the, read euen in the. pag, 95, lin, 6, for (that is the Lords way) read (that is the Lords) <hi>vvay.</hi> pag, 96, lin, 2, for (or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſiluer) read or fined) ſiluer. pag, 111, lin, 14, for (or inforcing of wrath) read (or inforcing of) <hi>wrath.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at London for</hi> Robert Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe <hi>in Paules Church-yard at the</hi> Signe of the Braſen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. 1596.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12612:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
